<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The deceived, and deceiving Quakers discovered. Their damnable heresies, horrid blasphemies, mockings, railings, unparallel'd deceit, and dishonestly laid open. In the discovery of which, is made known the pure use of the holy scriptures (which by them is denyed) the true Christ, and how he justifies, his second coming proved not to be already (as the Quaker affirms) also the resurrection from the dead, and the eternal judgement, and several other particulars that saints are required to be stedfast in. / Set forth especially for the good of those that are called out of the world, into the primitive order of the Gospel, but may be usefull for all people. By Matthew Caffyn a servant of the Lord, related to the Church of Christ near Horsham in Sussex, being an eye, and ear-witnesse. As wee have heard that Antichrist shall come, even now are there many antichrists, whereby we cannot but know that this is the last of the last time. Antichrist made known. Or, The Romish vvhore of Babylon proved not to bee the Antichrist, or man of sin, in seven particulars. 1 Who is this great whore of Babylon, and where her chief seat hath been, and is. 2 Her fall, and the means how and by whom. 3 What is the spirit of Antichrist, and who hath that spirit. 4 That the Antichrist will bee a single person. 5 The manner of his rising, and when. ... 7 Lastly, his fall, when, and by whom. By William Jeffery servant of the Church of Christ. Entered into the register book, kept by the Company of Stationers.</title>
            <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E873_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117938</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117938)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E873[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The deceived, and deceiving Quakers discovered. Their damnable heresies, horrid blasphemies, mockings, railings, unparallel'd deceit, and dishonestly laid open. In the discovery of which, is made known the pure use of the holy scriptures (which by them is denyed) the true Christ, and how he justifies, his second coming proved not to be already (as the Quaker affirms) also the resurrection from the dead, and the eternal judgement, and several other particulars that saints are required to be stedfast in. / Set forth especially for the good of those that are called out of the world, into the primitive order of the Gospel, but may be usefull for all people. By Matthew Caffyn a servant of the Lord, related to the Church of Christ near Horsham in Sussex, being an eye, and ear-witnesse. As wee have heard that Antichrist shall come, even now are there many antichrists, whereby we cannot but know that this is the last of the last time. Antichrist made known. Or, The Romish vvhore of Babylon proved not to bee the Antichrist, or man of sin, in seven particulars. 1 Who is this great whore of Babylon, and where her chief seat hath been, and is. 2 Her fall, and the means how and by whom. 3 What is the spirit of Antichrist, and who hath that spirit. 4 That the Antichrist will bee a single person. 5 The manner of his rising, and when. ... 7 Lastly, his fall, when, and by whom. By William Jeffery servant of the Church of Christ. Entered into the register book, kept by the Company of Stationers.</title>
                  <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
                  <author>Jeffery, William, 1616-1693. Antichrist made known.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.I. for Francis Smith, and are to bee sold at his shop in Flying-horse-Court in Fleetstreet, neer Chansery-Lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing lists this work as two separate items.</note>
                  <note>"Antichrist made know; or, The Romish VVhore of Babylon proved not to bee the Antichrist, or man of sin, in seven particulars." has caption title on p.63; register and pagination continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antichrist --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117938:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Deceived, and deceiving Quakers DISCOVERED.</p>
            <p>Their damnable Hereſies, horrid blaſphemies, mockings, railings, unparallel'd Deceit, and Diſhoneſty laid open.</p>
            <p>In the diſcovery of which, is made known the pure uſe of the holy Scriptures (which by them is denyed) the true Chriſt, and how he juſtifies, his ſecond coming proved not to be already (as the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker affirms) Alſo the Reſurrection from the dead, and the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal JUDGMENT, and ſeveral other particulars that Saints are required to be ſtedfaſt in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set forth eſpecially for the good of thoſe that are called out of the World, into the primitive order of the Goſpel, but may be uſefull for all people. By</hi> Matthew Caffyn <hi>a ſervant of the Lord, related to the Church of Chriſt near</hi> Horſham <hi>in</hi> Suffex, <hi>being an eye, and ear-witneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As wee have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts, whereby we cannot but know that this is the laſt of the laſt time.</p>
            <p>Antichriſt made known. OR, The Romiſh VVhore of Babylon proved not to bee the Antichriſt, or Man of Sin, In ſeven particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Who is this great Whore of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and where her chief Seat hath been, and is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Her Fall, and the means how and by whom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>What is the spirit of Antichriſt, and who hath that ſpirit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>That the Antichriſt will bee a ſingle perſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>The manner of his riſing, and when.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 <hi>Some of the great things hee will do.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 Laſtly, <hi>His Fall, when, and by whom.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Jeffery <hi>Servant of the Church of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Entred into the Regiſter book, kept by the Company of Stationers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Flying-horſe-Court in <hi>Fleet ſtreet,</hi> neer <hi>Chanſery</hi>-Lane. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117938:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117938:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, take notice, that the hour is comming and now is, that Satan in a more than ordinary manner doth transform himſelf into an Angel of Light, and ſhape his Miniſters into the ſimilitudes of Miniſters of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſo he may not only take faſter hold of thoſe that are already under his dominion, and blind their minds, leſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt ſhould (in the purity thereof) ſhine unto them; but alſo that hee may (if poſſible) deceive the very Elect, and cauſe them that have eſcaped the pollutions of the World, to bee again intangled therein, and overcome. Therefore thoſe exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo often repeated in the Scripture, to take heed, watch, and pray, &amp;c. are of great neceſſity, by all Saints, to bee in a ſpeciall manner regarded; for that Satan will endeavour to deceive ſuch, is moſt certain; And it is as certain that the moſt likely way and means that he hath to effect this his deſign, muſt bee by fair ſhewes of holineſſe, and excellent pretences of Piety, which is figured out in Scripture under the name of Sheeps cloathing, with which Chriſt ſaith the falſe Prophets (which are Satans Miniſters) ſhall bee attired. Therefore tis poſſible that a Chriſtian-like outſide may bee, in ſome, but a cover for an Antichriſtian ſpirit. And that Satan ſhould thus delude his Servants into ſuch a converſation that ſavoreth of ſobriety, ſelf-deny all, and a transformity from the World, in very many things, which are very eminent characters of Chriſtianity; I ſay, that the Devil ſhould delude ſome into a ſhew of ſuch things, is no more to bee admired at, than his acting forth himſelf in the Magicians of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to work miracles, much like to thoſe which God ſhewed by his ſervant <hi>Moſes.</hi> Yea the Apoſtle teſtifies, that in his dayes ſome did make reſiſtance to the truth after this manner, <hi>2 Tim. 3.8.</hi> and of ſome alſo that were deluded into a voluntary humility, and ſuch things as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth to have a ſhew of wiſdome in wil-worſhip, and humility, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting of the body, not in any honour to the ſatisfying of the fleſh. Now tis a kind of ſelf-denyall to neglect the body, and not to ſatisfie the deſires of the fleſh; And alſo to abstain from meats, which God hath created to bee received with thankſgiving, as he ſaith, <hi>1 Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2, 3.</hi> that ſome ſhould do, who yet were ſuch as had departed from the faith, and given
<pb facs="tcp:117938:3"/>heed to ſeducing ſpirits and Doctrins of Devils. And thus Satan by transforming his ſervants into ſuch ſhews, doth make them the more fit to advance his deceiving deſign amongſt the ſons of men; for hereby hee doth not only deceive them, but alſo furniſh them with ability to be DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEITFULL WORKERS to prevail upon others, <hi>2 Cor. 11.13.</hi> And of this ſort are thoſe people now called QVAKERS, whoſe deceitfull, and hereticall wayes (in part) are in this little volume preſented before thee (in anſwer to a book intituled, An untaught teacher witneſſed againſt) leſt thou ſhouldeſt by their ſubtle inſinuations and fair pretences of ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all, &amp;c. ſo far let out thy affections towards them, as not to try them in other things, which being throughly ſearched out, will prove them to bee thoſe deceivers which yee have heard ſhould come in the laſt dayes, of whoſe deceit (O reader) bee thou aware, and conſider that the deceiver cannot put away his braſs mony but by mixing it among good ſilver, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men may, if not circumſpect, bee unawares deceived. Wherefore bee CIRCV MSPECT, and ſtable in all thy wayes; And if through rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and due conſideration of this enſuing treatiſe, thou ſhalt bee the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fitted to diſcern truth from error, CHRIST from ANTICHRIST, and ſo (through grace) be the better enabled to ſtand faſt, the aim of mee herein is accompliſhed, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>An unworthy ſervant of Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of the eternal wel-fare of thy ſoul, MATTHEW CAFFYN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117938:3"/>
            <head>The Damnable Hereſies of the Quakers Diſcovered.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Friends, it doth not a little concern the People of God at this time to walk circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, <hi>having their Lights burning as wiſe Virgins,</hi> that they may be the approved of the Lord, and ſo the preſerved of the Lord in theſe laſt days, wherein the evil is great; juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may we be blamed (as others have been) by the Lord, if we diſcern not this time; which is, and much more will be full of peril, yea ſuch a time of trouble as never was ſince there was a Nation, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. in which the Myſtery of Iniquity that did in meaſure work in the Apoſtles days, ſhall be finiſhed, and the Man of Sin revealed the Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; which then was let, even till our days, by the power of the Kings of the earth, which withſtood the liberty of mens Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. but now the Lord hath removed it in this our Nation, and ſo we have (praiſed be the Lord) enjoyed much Liberty and Freedom; by means whereof the Goſpel of Jeſus hath been, and yet is declared among the Sons of Men; whereby divers have been fully convinced of the Truth of Chriſt, ſome of which have denied themſelves and become obedient: and other ſome have put from them the words of everlaſting life; yea notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the goodneſs of God, together with his long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and long patience towards them, have not received the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved; for which cauſe God hath ſent a ſtrong deluſion, that they (as conſidered oppoſing Grace) might beleeve a Lye, and ſo be damned, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. wherefore in the fear of the Lord God who thus judgeth, let us grow, and abound in pure love unto the Lord, and his Truth, that we may ſtand in theſe laſt perilous days; wherein Satan will work
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117938:4"/>not only with power, but with all Power, Signs, and lying Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; not only with deceit, but with all deceivableneſs of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9, 10. O then let us be watchful, and with all care awake to righteouſneſs; putting on the whole Armour of God, that we may be able to withſtand all the wiles of the Devil, for the time is come wherein we muſt wraſtle againſt the Powers of Darkneſs, and Spiritual wickedneſs, which is crept into Sheeps cloathing, having ſuch fair pretences, as that thoſe that are not in ſome meaſure acquainted with their double-meaning expreſſions, cannot ſuddenly finde out the iniquity of the Myſtery. Wherefore I concluded it neceſſary, having ſome experience of the deceitful, pernicious ways of the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> to ſignifie to all, what I have been an ear, and eye-witneſs of concerning them, whom we ſee many follow, whereby we hear the way of Truth is evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and the profeſſours thereof ſlandered, and falſly accuſed; but this is, that the Scripture might be fulfilled, which teſtifies of the coming of the Wicked one, before the coming of the Juſt one, (the Lord Jeſus) <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3, 4. who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him with the brightneſs of his coming, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaith, That there is ſuch a light in every man (which they ſay is a meaſure of Chriſt) that leads, and guides into all the ways of God, without the Scripture, or any outward Teachings; and</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Nayler) <hi>is the ONLY revealer of the Goſpel; as appears in his Book called,</hi> Satans deſign diſcovered, <hi>pag.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us minde the Law, and Teſtimony, for if they do not herein ſpeak according to it, it is becauſe they have no light in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, that there is ſuch a knowledge, or light in man (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered with the continual voyce of the Heavens, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.) as to know that there is a God, and in meaſure alſo what is juſt, and good, according to that he was firſt Created in, and ſo in meaſure evil, when he walks contrary to this light; and to this was added, (in the days of <hi>Moſes</hi>) the written Law, which remains to us; ſhewing to us (as it did to them) things that are MORE EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLENT, being inſtructed out of the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.18. ſin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appearing by it exceeding ſinful, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.13. for had not the Law ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet, Paul</hi> ſignifieth, that he had not known luſt to be ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. wherefore he concludes, that the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117938:4"/>
               <hi>Jew</hi> had great advantage, and profit above the <hi>Gentile,</hi> and chiefly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that unto them were committed the Oracles of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2. now the <hi>Gentiles</hi> having not the Law, were indeed a Law unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) but to the <hi>Jews</hi> that had the written Law hee ſaith no ſuch thing; but (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) THIS BOOK of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate therein day and night, that thou mayeſt obſerve to do according to all that is written therein, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.8. wherefore it follows, that the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> conſidered HAVING NOT THE LAW (mark) were a Law unto themſelves; that is, in reference to ſuch things as were contained in the written Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the deeds of which the Apoſtle afterwards ſaith, No fleſh ſhall be juſtified in his ſight, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.10.5. it being weak through the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. that is, man being by the Fall under manifold Curſes, is often over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and acts contrary to his knowledge from the Law, while his Nature ſtill inclines to its firſt eaſe, pleaſure, and delight; and ſo by the Law he is condemned, for by it is the knowledge of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. wherefore no righteouſneſs, no Soul-peace by it, for he that DOTH theſe things ſhall live by them, ſaith the Law; the Soul is wounded, and nothing will cure it, but the knowledge of remiſſion of ſins, which is made known by outward means; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was ſaid of <hi>John,</hi> that he ſhould go before the face of the Lord, to give knowledge of Salvation unto his people by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.77. which was to be preached by the Commandement of Chriſt to all Nations by the APOSTLES, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. yea at the beginning was it made known by outward diſcoveries, for it is recorded of <hi>Abel</hi> that hee was righteous by faith; now, ſaith the Apoſtle, there is but one faith, and this comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16, 17, 18. which people in Primitive times heard, as ſpoken UNTO them divers ways; and ſo whoever of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that ſought for glory, honour, and immortality (having faith therein by hearing) and in the mean while, patiently continued in doing well accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law written in their hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. they ſo belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving were excuſed in themſelves, but if otherwiſe, accuſed; for ſo, and no otherwiſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> that had the (written) Law could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by it, for by the deeds thereof no fleſh ſhall bee juſtified; wherefore God at ſundry times, in divers manners ſpake unto the Fathers BY THE PROPHETS, the way of Juſtification, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. Wherefore, ſaith the Prophet, ſhould yee not hear the words
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117938:5"/>which the Lord hath cryed by the former Prophets? <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.7. if ye will not heat the words of my ſervants the Prophets, then will I make this houſe as <hi>Shiloh,</hi> Jer. 26.4, 5, 6. ſhewing plainly, that God did not, (as by himſelf dwelling in all men) ſpeak to them his whole counſel, but unto them, by his Prophets; and Judgements are threatned upon the not hearing of their words, not upon the ſlighting of ſuch a light within; and beſides, Faith is ſaid to come through their words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16, 17, 18. no where is it ſaid, no not by any of the Prophets, that God required men to wait altogether upon ſuch a light within; yet ſaith <hi>Nayler,</hi> that is the ONLY revealer of the Goſpel; 'tis plain the Prophets had another ſpirit; for <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> bids the people ſtand in the ways, and ſee, and ask for the old paths, where is the good way, and walk therein, and you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall find reſt for your ſouls, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.16. now if the good way, and all the way were within them, why were they to ask for it, and to enquire, ſtanding in the wayes? and not rather to ſtand ſtill ſilent, waiting upon the light within; the wiſe muſt needs judge, the reaſon was, becauſe the will of the Lord in order to ſoul-peace, and reſt, was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by outward means; wherefore incline your ear, and come unto mee, hear, and your ſoul ſhall live, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. which when <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> neglected, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> complains, ſaying, Who hath beleeved OUR report? the Quaker cryeth, <hi>who hath waited upon the light within, the light within?</hi> another report, wherefore another Spirit.</p>
            <p>Though we may not deny, but that through the report of the Prophets they were inlightened within<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from whence they were to act; ſo faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God; now the Quaker may not ſay that word is Chriſt; (the light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, that in order to that Faith which comes by hearing; their ſound went into all the earth, and THEIR words unto the ENDS of the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18. now (THEIR) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be aſcribed to one Preacher ſingly; therefore is not ſuch a light within, which is but one; and if the Quaker ſlight this, he is more inexcuſable than other men, ſince he hath ſo far ſearched, as to find that (you) relates not to a ſingle perſon; alſo by this ſaying of <hi>Paul</hi> we may conſider that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo were inlightened by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-preaching Prophets, who ſometimes were to go unto the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to miniſter unto them, as witneſſeth <hi>Jonahs</hi> going to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and moſt evident it is, that there were ſome proſelited out of every Nation under Heaven to the way of the Lord, which the <hi>Jews</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117938:5"/>
               <hi>Act.</hi> 2.5. yet the <hi>Jew</hi> had a priviledge in this, but where much is given, much is required; moreover if we look yet farther back, I ſay as I ſaid before, that there is not to be found ſuch an admonition, no not from the very beginning, as that men ſhould wholly depend upon a teacher within; this I find, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.14. that <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam</hi> propheſied of the Lords comming WITH (he ſaith not in) ten thouſand of his Saints, as the Quaker pleads; <hi>Noah</hi> alſo is ſaid to be a Preacher of Righteouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. and through his obedience in preparing the ark hee is ſaid thereby to condemn the world, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7. alſo it appears that the Lord ſhewed his wrath, and made his power known upon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and his mighty Hoaſt, that his name (through that memorable act) might be declared throughout all the earth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16. alſo we find that God did ſpeak unto <hi>Moſes</hi> out of a cloudy pillar which deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſight of the people; unto <hi>Abraham</hi> he ſpake by an Angel from Heaven; and the common expreſſion in Scripture to ſignify the way of Gods ſpeaking is this; the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> unto <hi>Iſaac,</hi> unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> but I find not where it is ſaid, that God did ſpeak in his <hi>people,</hi> his whole will and counſel, as the Quaker affirms.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>That which may bee known of God is manifeſt in man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lawſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> informs us that which may be known of God is manifeſt in (or to) man (ſaith the Notes) ſo alſo he informs us how it comes there, and by that we find him to have a ſpirit differing from <hi>Lawſons:</hi> for <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that God hath ſhewed it unto man by the things that are made, whereby is clearly underſtood his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall power, and God-head from the Creation, for day unto day, night unto night it ſheweth knowledge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.2. and ſo is man without excuſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. that is in reſpect of knowing there is a God: all which ſhews that there is not ſuch a light within as he ſpeaks of, becauſe mans inexcuſableneſſe is aſcribed to his neglect of due reſpect to outward means, wherefore <hi>Lawſon</hi> that talks ſo much of the tongue of the learned, is found unlearned himſelf by wreſting the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Conſider alſo I pray you, from the dayes of <hi>John</hi> the baptiſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wards, and you ſhall find all the Scriptures unanimouſly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict this Principle of theirs. <hi>John</hi> is ſaid to be a burning and a ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light, being appointed of God to GIVE KNOWLEDGE of ſalvation unto his people, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.77. and to prepare his wayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, which had been uſeleſſe, <hi>had the people a knowledge of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117938:6"/>all his wayes by an internal light;</hi> yea <hi>John</hi> himſelf (though none grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he born of women) depended not upon ſuch a light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to know all things, for he ſent two of his Diſciples to Chriſt to know whether he were the Chriſt that ſhould come, or that they ſhould look for another (having a ſign given him before, that, on whomſoever he ſaw the Spirit deſcending, and remaining, was the baptiſer with the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 1.33.) and this depending upon out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſcoveries, Chriſt-himſelf eſtabliſhed by ſending back a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage conſiſting only of externals; the blind receiving ſight, the lame walking, the lepers cleanſed, &amp;c. which the two Diſcipies ſaw, and heard, theſe things Chriſt returned for <hi>Johns</hi> ſatisfaction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.5. in the dayes of <hi>John,</hi> Chriſt teſtified that he was the light of the World, not the Spirit in him only, but HE as he was the ſon of man, the intended Sacrifice of God for to dye for the life of the World; HE thus conſidered went from place to place preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdome, informing perſons particularly of their duties, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.7. chap. not commending them to a Teacher within, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>John</hi> the preparer of his way, when the publicans and ſouldiers came to him and asked him what they ſhould do, but taught them their duties, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.11, 12, 13. and as Chriſt perſonally taught his Diſciples, and the people, ſo alſo he confirmed what he declared by outward miracles, which many ſeeing beleeved on him, <hi>John</hi> 11.45. and others which heard and ſaw ſuch works done by him which no other man did, and beleeved not, Chriſt pronounceth inexcuſable, having no cloak for their ſin, <hi>John</hi> 15.22, 24. being ſuch as <hi>John</hi> admires at, <hi>John</hi> 12.37. ſaying, THOUGH he had done ſo many miracles before them, YET they beleeved not on him; Some, Chriſt ſaid were cleanſed by what hee, as the ſon of man, ſaid unto them, <hi>John</hi> 15.3. other ſome were without excuſe, ſubject to the Judgement, becauſe they received not his words which he ſpake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>John</hi> 12.48. what leſs oh friends can theſe things import, than that the words of Chriſt thus conſidered, did work convince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments within men of the truth? conſidering that the rejecting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of rendred them inexcuſable; if a light within (in their ſenſe) be the only Revealer, then <hi>John</hi> had no cauſe to admire in reference to the many miracles, but rather in reſpect of the Light being rejected which Chriſt ſet up within them, without ſuch outward manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; nay indeed he had no cauſe to admire at them more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all having (as they ſay) a Light within leading in all the wayes of God; but moſt evident it is that Chriſt hath otherwiſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117938:6"/>appointed to make known the Goſpel, as appears by his ſimilitude about the ſower, who ſaith, Chriſt went FORTH to ſow, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.3. went OUT to ſow, <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.3. contradicting the Quaker who ſaith the ſower is dwelling in all, godly and ungodly (though the Sower be ſaid to be the SON OF MAN, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.37.) wherefore when Chriſt ſent his twelve Apoſtles to the loſt ſheep of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he ſaid, that it ſhould be more tollerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> in the day of Judgement, than for that City that ſhould not receive THEIR WORDS, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.14. yea when his very Diſciples were blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in reſpect of their ignorance, he charges it not for neglecting a Teacher within, but ſaith, Oh fools and ſlow of heart to beleeve all that the Prophets have ſpoken, and to make them wiſe, he expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Scriptures to them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.25, 27. upbraiding their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leef alſo, becauſe they beleeved not THEM (he ſaith not Light within) but them which had ſeen him after he was riſen, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.14. now when Chriſt was to aſcend, he authorized his Servants to go, and teach all Nations to obſerve all things which he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, marke, not to turn them to a Teacher within, but to teach them all things; who accordingly went and teſtified that God did beſeech people by them, and that they in Chriſts STEAD prayed perſons to be reconciled to God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. yea declaring the whole counſel of God, the ſumme of which is, that Chriſt ſent his Servants to teach all things which he had commanded them, they accordingly taught his whole counſel, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.27. yet ſaith the Quaker, the Light in every man is the ONLY Teacher: Judge yee that are wiſe. Moreover 'tis ſaid that the Church of the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> received of the Apoſtles how to walk, and to pleaſe God, yet not as the words of men, but (as it is in truth) the Word of God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.1, 2, 13. and theſe were the elect of God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4. yet not thought by the Apoſtle capable by any Light within them (in an ordinary way) to comprehend all things relating to their faith, wherefore he prayed night and day EXCEEDINGLY that he might ſee their faces, and PERFECT that which was lacking in their faith, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. alſo <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Saints at <hi>Rome,</hi> Rom. 1.11. ſaid, that he longed to ſee them, to impart ſome ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gift that they might be eſtabliſhed; now if <hi>Paul</hi> had been of the Quakers ſpirit, he need not ſo exceedingly deſired to ſee them, or to write unto them upon that account, becauſe their (alone Teacher) and leader towards perfection was alwaies in them; needleſs I ſay, except it had been to exhort them to keep cloſe to their Teacher
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117938:7"/>within, but neither this do we find was their aim in writing, neither was it their aim in deſiring to ſee them, but that they might be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, &amp; perfected in their faith through what they delivered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that as the Apoſtles gave the Churches to know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, ſo alſo they directed them to wait upon the Lord who gives the increaſe, that by him they might be enabled to walk up accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what they knew, through their miniſtry, their miniſtry I ſay, becauſe it agrees with the Scriptures, which teſtifies, that by them was made manifeſt the ſavour of his knowledge in every place, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. and ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> if OUR Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, who are blinded, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine UNTO them, not from a Teacher within, but from the Apoſtles, who plainly affirms, that they were to give the Light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus. God having firſt ſhined in their hearts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4, 6. that is in the hearts of <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> who ſent that Epiſtle, who were enlightened, yea both of them, through outward teachings; <hi>Paul</hi> in an extraordinary manner by the Lord Jeſus was changed in his mind to beleeve in him, which makes him ſay, that the Goſpel was not taught him by man, but by the revelation of Jeſus; who (ſaith <hi>Luke</hi>) appeared UNTO him, and ſpake UNTO him, a Light ſhining round ABOUT him from HEAVEN, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.3, 4, 17. and by him was he commanded to go into <hi>Dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcus,</hi> and there he ſhould be told of all things which were appointed for him to do, <hi>Act.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.10. not by a Light within him, but by <hi>Ananias</hi> a certain Diſciple, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 14, 15, 16. thus <hi>Paul,</hi> being inſtructed, went forth preaching the Goſpel, through which, <hi>Timothy</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned in the Truth, and ſo commonly called by <hi>Paul</hi> his SON in the Faith, 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 1.2. even as <hi>Oneſimus</hi> was, whom <hi>Paul</hi> BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GOT in his bonds, <hi>Phile.</hi> 10. by all this we may learn that the Miniſters of Chriſt were by their miniſtry to make known the Lords will, yea moreover the Churches of old were to mark the walkings of the Apoſtles, as an ENSAMPLE to them; <hi>Paul</hi> commanding them to do thoſe things which they had both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeen in him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.4.9. and to this purpoſe agrees alſo his words to <hi>Timothy,</hi> give attendance to reading, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. wherefore falſe and erronious is that ſpirit which bids men give attendance to a Light within, as their ONLY Teacher.</p>
            <p>Wherefore hold faſt the counſel of the Spirit of God, and give at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance unto reading the Scriptures, being by a good argument
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117938:7"/>provoked thereunto, even that they are able to make us wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation through Faith in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. for even unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving men are required by Chriſt to ſearch the Scriptures, wherein they thought they had eternal life, but they were miſtaken, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſearch (ſaith he) for they teſtify of mee, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. plainly ſhewing, that the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Teſtimony of Scripture was to rectify their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings which if they had beleeved, they would have belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved mee (ſaith Chriſt) FOR HE WROTE OF MEE, <hi>verſe</hi> 46. but ſaith (Antichriſt) if ye would beleeve in the Light within as your only Teacher, then ye ſhould be led by it up to Chriſt. Mark ye, I pray, the great difference betwixt the Doctrin of Chriſt, and the Doctrin of the Quakers, who make void the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt, by their extolling an internal Light as the only Teacher, which is their OWN tradition, it being tryed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Spirit of Light indeed which dwelt in the Apoſtles; as you may further learn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom what <hi>Pauls</hi> Spirit led him unto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14, 15. unto whom he hoped to go ſhortly, but if he tarried long, that he might KNOW how to behave himſelf in the houſe of God, he WROTE an Epiſtle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and therein he did not counſel him to wait upon a Teacher within (as is the ſubſtance of the Quakers Epiſtles) but particularly informed him of his duty, as will appear to him that reads the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with due reſpect thereunto; now if there be ſuch an internall Light that makes known all things, judge I pray you, what ground <hi>Paul</hi> had to queſtion <hi>Timothys</hi> knowing thoſe things in his abſence, conſidering alſo how eminent in grace <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mothy</hi> was, even ſo diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed unto the work of the Lord, as that <hi>Paul</hi> had NO man like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. you even he was to read <hi>Paul</hi> Epiſtle (which was Scripture) and for that end, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w he ought to walk in the houſe of the Lord. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> now to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Scriptures that wee may know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſelves? God forbid! God forbid! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> peoples ignorance to their not knowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> erre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not knowing the Scriptures, nor th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 29. and upbraideth them with this qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> have ye not read? <hi>Mat</hi> 12.3, 5. <hi>chap.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the will of Chriſt was, that men ſhould lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries; which if you ſeriouſly conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> blame, in caſe they ought not to have learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Scriptures, which is ſaid by <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117938:8"/>for Doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the man of God may be perfect, THOROWLY fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unto all good work; all which Scripture is given by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from God, and ſo originally God is the Teacher of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yea of all, but as it is written, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. God beſeecheth you BY US, in Chriſts STEAD.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Spirit (an internal Teacher) ſaith the Quaker from that in</hi> Joh. 16.13. <hi>is that which is to lead into all truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt indeed there ſpeaks of the Spirits leading into all Truth, but it is to be obſerved that it was ſpoken unto ſuch as were ſo far before led into Truth by Chriſts perſonall preaching, as that they were pronounced clean through the words which he had ſpoken unto them, <hi>John</hi> 15.3. Wherefore in an eſpeciall manner he there ſpeaks of thoſe many things which the Diſciples then could not bear; as is moſt plain, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. and beſides the acts of the Diſciples, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their directions ſent to the Churches, when they were led by this Spirit, are left to us in Scripture; yet wee may not deny but that the Spirit, in whom he dwels, is a Teacher, evidently, and particularly laying before the ſoul the privy deceit, and evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of his heart, and leading him to a mortification thereof; (he being waited upon) and alſo revealing many other uſefull things, which unto the natural man is fooliſhneſſe; but judge Oh friends how far off this is from the Quakers purpoſe, who exhorts all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſons of the World whatſoever to depend upon a light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, when as Chriſt in plain words ſaith that the World CANNOT receive this Spirit whereof we ſpeak, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. the promiſe thereof (ſo as to dwell with a ſoul as a comforter) being to obedient beleeving perſons, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.5.32. <hi>John</hi> 14.15, 16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. even ſuch as walk up in duty towards God according to the inſtruction of the holy Scriptures; Oh how great then is the darkneſs of him that talks ſo much of the Light! and counſels all to depend upon it alone; which is contrary to the counſel both of Chriſt the true Light, the Angel of God, and the holy Apoſtles; For when the Diſciples inquired of Chriſt What ſign there ſhould be of his comming (by which it is plain, they diſtruſted that Light they had within) he directs them not to a Light within, but readily anſwers their deſires; to which agrees alſo the relation of <hi>Sauls</hi> converſion; ſo alſo when <hi>Cornelius</hi> cryed out ſaying, what is it Lord? the Angel of God bid him ſend for <hi>Peter,</hi> and HE ſhould tell him what he ought to do, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.4.5, 6. ſo alſo when thoſe that were pricked
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117938:8"/>in heart, ſaid unto the Apoſtles what ſhall we do? <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>Peter</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects them not to an internal Teacher, but teaches them himſelf, <hi>verſ.</hi> 38. Likewiſe when the Jaylour cryed out, ſaying, what muſt I do to he ſaved? <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> neither directed him to a Light within, but THEY ſpake unto him the Word of the Lord; likewiſe when the Eunuch ſaid, how can I underſtand, except ſome man guide mee? <hi>Act.</hi> 8.31. <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid, not as the Quaker doth, that the Light within is to guide into all Truth, but himſelf began at the ſame Scripture, and preached unto him Jeſus; conſider I pray ye how fair an occaſion in all theſe inſtances there was for ſuch counſel, namely to wait upon the Light within, in caſe it had been the Lords pleaſure ſo to teach men; but we find another Doctrin, and conſider that Jeſus Chriſt is the ſame, yeſterday, and to day, and for ever.</p>
            <p>Wherefore be counſelled not to bee carried about with DIVERS and STRANGE Doctrins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8, 9. for this I affirm with all confidence, that it is not to be found from the beginning of <hi>Geneſit,</hi> unto the end of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> that either Chriſt, or any of the holy men of God, from the beginning of the Creation, that did at any time counſel ignorant, ſelf-ſerving perſons, which had not been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enlightened within, through outward teachings, to wait upon a Light within them, as the ONLY revealer of the Goſpel; Chriſt indeed gave this counſel to ſome, that they ſhould walk in the Light, while they had the Light, but they were ſuch as were with Chriſt the Light, and had heard him preaching the Kingdome of God often, and had ſeen ſo many miracles done by him, that <hi>John</hi> admires at their unbeleef, <hi>John</hi> 12.37. wherefore this ſhelters not their opinion, and ſo it remains naked; an Hereſy proceeding from the fleſh, which, by reaſon of its pride, would not ſubmit unto the ſelf-denying Laws of Chriſt, but hath found out a way to paſſe by it, even by turning the Scriptures into myſterious ſenſes, and ſo makes void many plain Truths of Chriſt, by their dreams which they tell every man to his neighbour, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.27. which at the time of awaking will appear even to them, to be a meer deceitfull dream, proceeding from him, who pretends himſelf an Angel of Light; but greater is he that is in us, than he that is in the World, whereby the Quaker is diſcovered in his nakedneſle, and Chriſt the true Light of the World more and more gloriouſly made known unto us, even him who is a Light indeed, not as <hi>John</hi> who was a ſhining Light to <hi>Iſrael</hi> only, but the glory of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and a Light
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117938:9"/>to lighten the <hi>Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les</hi> alſo, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.32. being for ſalvation unto the ends of the earth, a Light that lighteth every man that com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> the World; from whence the Quakers would gather that Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the Light is within all, as their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly ſeacher, but <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Barnahas</hi> being of another ſpirit, gathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thing, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap> thence, ſaing, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 13.46.10, we turn to the <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiles</hi> or ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> com a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ded us, ſaying, I have ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Light o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Gentiles, verſe</hi> 47 So far were they from beleev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thence, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as the alone Teacher in men, that they conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Gentiles</hi> in Chriſts STEAD, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y have the ſame Spirit which the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> judge y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> wiſe.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Children of the New Teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>every man his Brother, ſaying, Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>th them all things, ſo that they need not that any man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>each th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Law written in their hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Abrahams</hi> ſeed, with whom the old C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>enan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was made, was Children thereof by generation, which. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth by the bond-woman and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; even <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hmae<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who was born after the ſleſh: and being ſo in covenant, they had need to be taught to know the Lord; but the children of this more glorious adminiſtration, are not ſo accounted of, but otherwiſe, even by regeneration, and ſuch none can be, till they firſt know the Lord, and ſuch (conſidered AS children of the New Covenant) need not teach one another to know the Lord, for all ſuch do know him, as did the Church of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> whom <hi>Paul</hi> calls children, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the bond woman, but of the free, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.31. (that is of the New Teſtament) yet conſider they were ſuch as heard the Goſpel from the Apoſtles, who ſaid unto that people, that if wee or an Angel from Heaven preach any other Goſpel unto you, than that which WE have preached unto you, let him be accurſed; yea at that time, when they were children of the New Teſtament, they were alſo to give heed unto the Scriptures for direction; for otherwiſe <hi>Paul</hi> would not have ſent unto them an Epiſtle in Scripture, and therein tell them that as many as walked according to this rule, peace be on them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. yet this their reſpect to the teachings of the Apoſtles, and the Scriptures, in things pertaining to the Faith, and order of the Goſpel, doth not in the leaſt contradict Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of writing his Law in their hearts, for ſuch they are, that have a promiſe of his Spirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. and are the Temple, wherein God dwelling by his Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16, writes his Law, even in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117938:9"/>their hearts particularly, and plainly makes known his ROYAL LAW, that ſo together by the power of the Spirit, ſuch may have the Righteouſneſſe of the Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fulfilled in them, they walking not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4. wherefore it ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, that though the Children of the New Teſtament need not to be taught to knew the Lord, yet have need to be builded up in the knowledge of the Lord, for <hi>Timothy</hi> knew the Lord, (as his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) yet <hi>Paul</hi> ſends Scripture unto him that he MIGHT KNOW how to behave himſelf in the Church of God, 1 <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 3.14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>15. and alſo by Scripture ſtirs up the Saints to edify ONE AN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>HER, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11. and ſaith <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> grow in the knowledge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. to them that k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew the Lord 2 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> 1.3. and this might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the practice of them <hi>John</hi> wrote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſaid againſt it; for though he judged them ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>t in ſpiritual gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, and in the knowledge of the Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>an dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>its (which the there ſpeaketh of) as to conclude there was no abſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſſity for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any other of the Apoſtles to write unto them y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this is far from ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they ought not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o edifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ther, as other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s were to do; the anoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing indeed was dwelling in them, and ſo was he in other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, that were enjoyned to edifie one another, even the Spirit of truth, whoſe gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ivers, the manifeſtations whereof are given to every man to profit withall; he that techeth is to wait <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and he that exh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rteth on exhortation <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 12 7, 8. theſe with other of the gifts of the Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it appeat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Churen was enriched with, and ſo in a capacity to preſs forward notwithſtanding all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions) as good Stewards miniſtring one to another the manifold diſcoveries of Truth.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Apoſtles were indeed to go unto the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>but it was to turn them from darkneſſe to the Light within, through which the word of Faith which they preached was nigh them, even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n their mouths, and in their hearts before, as a Light ſhining in darkneſs, but darkneſs comprehended it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Surely the Meſſengers of Chriſt that were led by one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, had but one meſſage, which was to go and teach all Nations, baptiſing them, &amp;c. teaching them to obſerve ALL things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad commanded them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.20. To which agrees the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 15.19. where he teſtifieth, that from <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and round about unto <hi>Illyricum,</hi> HE had FULLY preached the Goſpel of Chriſt, and moreover <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith, that if we, or an Angel from Heaven preach any OTHER Goſpel than that which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117938:10"/>WE have preached, let him be accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. and this Goſpel was not in every mans heart before thus preached, or by ſome other outward diſcoveries, for <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies, that he ſtrived to preach the Goſpel, where Chriſt was not named, but as it is written, to whom he hath not been ſpoken of, they ſhall ſee, and they that have not heard, ſhall underſtand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.20, 21. wherein it is very obſervable, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ignorance is not aſcribed to their darkneſſe, not comprehending what was ſpoken in them, but to the want of ſome to ſpeak unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m to whom Chriſt had not been ſpoken of (as come in the fleſh) to which agrees theſe words of the Apoſtle, How ſhall they beleeve in him, of whom they have not heard? that is, hath not heard by an outward miniſtry, as plainly appears by his continued queſtions; how ſhall THEY preach except THEY be ſent? as it is written, how beautifull are the feet of THEM that preach the Goſpel? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15. wherefore not by the Light within, which even in our adverſaries ſenſe is but one; (yet by this do we not limit God to this his ordinary way, and ſo make void his ſpeaking by Angels, or otherwiſe UNTO men at his pleaſure) and further, if you conſider, the word of Faith cannot be ſaid to be in mens hearts, and in their MOUTHES, and they not comprehend it; nay it is no better than an unlearned, ignorant myſtery, which cannot bee received by any, except ſenſualiſts, that have not the Spirit, <hi>Jud.</hi> 19. for they that ſo poſſeſſe the word of Faith, are at preſent in a fit condition to beleeve with the heart, and alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe what they beleeve, with their mouths, and even ſo ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> in that place, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. that if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhall beleeve in thine heart, &amp;c. thou ſhalt bee ſaved.</p>
            <p>Now we know that a man cannot make confeſſion to Salvation with his mouth, of ſuch things which in his heart he comprehends not; wherefore well obſerve that ſaying of <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 10.8. and you ſhall finde, that though he ſay that the word of Faith which he (with others) preached, was nigh them, even in their mouthes and hearts, yet he doth not ſay that it was there before it was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto them, while they were in ignorance and blindneſs; for at that time when he ſpake theſe words unto them, they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted perſons, ſuch as beleeved through <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching before, and perſwading them both out of the Scripture of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and out of the Scripture of the Prophets, from morning till evening, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.23, 24. which is agreeable with that which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iſrael,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117938:10"/>Deut.</hi> 30.14. even that the Word was nigh unto him, in his mouth and heart, that he might do it; but moſt plain it is that <hi>Iſrael</hi> was enlightned within through the written Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which there he ſpeaks of, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. which he preached unto them, ſaying, That the words which I command thee ſhall bee in thy Heart, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6. and theſe my words ſhall yee lay up in your hearts and ſouls, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18. after which means he ſaid, and well he might, that the Commandement which I command thee, is not hidden from thee, but is in thy mouth, and in thy heart; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtill it remains that the Lord in all Ages did teach men, through outward diſcoveries, and not that they were led into all truth by a light within them, as the only revealer of the Goſpel, as ſaith the Quaker; and ſo he is tried, and ſound to have ſpoken contrary to the Law, and Teſtimony; wherefore I conclude that it is becauſe there is no light in them, though they ſo much talk of light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaith, That the Scriptures are not a rule, whereby men may know the Will of Chriſt, as often they have ſpoken, being preſt to it, and as appears in</hi> Tho. Lauſons <hi>Book, called,</hi> The untaught Teacher, pag. 6, 7, 8. <hi>wherein he repearts my ſaying, That the Scriptures doth ſo farre reveal the minde of God, and Chriſt, to a Creature, as that hee walking up to its revelation, to his lives end, with a ſingle heart, ſhould be ſaved; this I ſay he repeats, and publiſhes as great Hereſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God who at ſundry times, and divers manners, ſpake unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken to us by his Son, who in his own perſon (while perſonally upon earth) inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ſons of men, exhorting them to repent, and turn from ſin, pronouncing them everlaſtingly bleſſed that ſo did. and followed him; unto whom he particularly revealed his Will, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5, 6, 7. chap. ſaying, that he was a wiſe man, building upon a rock, that heard his ſayings, and did them, and that he was a fooliſh man that heard his ſayings, and did them not; which plainly ſhews, that the words of Chriſt proceeding from himſelf was a rule to lead perſons then in the way of Salvation; and ſo is made good that ſaying, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation, which at the FIRST began to be ſpoken by the Lord Jeſus; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Diſciples took in hand to ſet forth in order a Declaration, (by writing) of thoſe things which Chriſt had ſpoken unto them, which was moſt ſurely beleeved by them, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1. to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117938:11"/>whom he ſhewed himſelf alive after his Paſſion, being ſeen of them forty days, ſpeaking of the things per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aining to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. who alſo went forth after his aſcenſion into the Nations, an ſpreached that Word of Truth unto them, which was FIRST ſpoken by the Lord to themſelves, teaching them to ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whatſoever Chriſt had commanded them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> commiſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. God alſo bearing them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, Miracies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and divers girts of the Holy Gho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Heb.</hi> 2 3. th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny obtained like precious faith with the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tles 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts of the Apoſtles <hi>Luke</hi> alſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> writing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y all which Scriptures together with the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> unto the perſons thus converted, the preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> made man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſt; and by the Scriptures of the Prop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Commandement of God) made know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Nations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> obedience of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.25, 26. whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>OBILITY in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of <hi>Berea</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> daily whether thoſe things were ſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, which indeed had been a very igno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of them had not the Scriptures been (as a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> know the truth of what was preached, as it appears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it is ſaid, that therefore many of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or which cauſe Chriſt bids the <hi>Jew,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaving, That if they had beleeved the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſes</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I have to beleeved on him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39.46, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7 t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t if they beleeved not in him, the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rds which he ſpake (which are now in Scripture) ſhould judge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t day, <hi>Jo.</hi> 12.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 48. And ſaith <hi>Paul, Sylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>morh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y man obey not OVR word, by this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle (which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>criou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that man, and have no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with him that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned; now that the diſobedience to the Scriptures ſhould render men ſubjects of ſo great ſhame in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the laſt day Chriſt ſhould alſo judge them by it (even the words which he hath ſpoken) and yet not a rule now to walk by is altogether incredible; the ways of God being juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and righteous altogether, will might the Quaker be aſhamed, were he not given over to beleeve Lyes, while hee affirms that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is not a rule whereby to know the Will of Chriſt ſince <hi>Luke</hi> ſignifies no other end, in his writing in order a Declaration of the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings, and loings of Chriſt, but that the CERTAINTY THEREOF MIGHT BE KNOWN, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1, 3, 4. Theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117938:11"/>are written that yee MIGHT BELEEVE, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31. wherefore ſaith Chriſt, O fools, and ſlow of heart to beleeve all that the Prophets have ſpoken; Oh then let us be wiſe, like the holy men of old, who eſteemed the Scriptures holy (in reference to the uſe thereof) able to make MEN WISE TO SALVATION through faith which is in Chriſt, it being profitable for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin (which in Engliſh is teaching) for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs, that the man of God may bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. yea ſo great was their reſpect to the Scriptures, that though <hi>Peter</hi> was an eye witneſs of the Majeſty of Chriſt in his Tranſfiguration upon the Mount, wherein was preſented the manner of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, yet ſaith he, We have a MORE SURE WORD OF PROPHECY, that was in the Scripture, as appears 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16, 17.19, 20. whereunto (O friends) we ſhall do well if wee take heed; for whatſoever was written afore time, was written for our LEARNING, that we through patience, and COMFORT of the Scriptures, might have hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>The Scripture is not the rule</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Lawſon) <hi>for no man can come to the Son except the Father draw him; and no man can come to the Father but by the Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Gods way to draw men is by the cords of his great love, manifeſted in Chriſt, which the ſervants of Chriſt, in Chriſts ſtead are to publiſh to the Nations, perſwading men thereby to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God; and this is (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) as though GOD DID BESEECH YOU BY US, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. the Saints indeed are ſaid to be the called of God; but ſaith <hi>Paul BY OVR GOSPEL,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.14. ſo alſo it is ſaid of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> That they were called of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. yet ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> In Chriſt Jeſus I have begotten you through the Goſpel; I have eſpouſed you to one hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. and ſo it is that as God did ſpeak unto the Fathers BY THE PROPHETS, ſo now by his Servants in Chriſts ſtead, who are to miniſter, by his Spirit, that which was FIRST ſpoken by the Lord himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. who ſpake not of himſelf, but what God the Father commanded him, and ſo it was that the Saints (to their commendation) received the words of the Apoſtle, not as the words of men, but (AS IT IS IN TRUTH) the word of God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. wherefore the Quaker (ſuppoſing that God himſelf in men is their Teacher only) erres not knowing the Scriptures; for <hi>Iſrael</hi> was willing to be taught, yet ſaid they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117938:12"/>let not God ſpeak with us, but ſpeak thou with us, (<hi>Moſes</hi>) and we will hear, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.19. and in this they well ſaid, ſaith God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.28.</p>
            <p>Moſt true it is, that no man can come to the Father, but by the Son, who offered up himſelf to death, that we might have life, by whoſe ſtripes we are healed; without his blood there is no remiſſion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. by him alſo we have acceſs unto the Father, who at his right hand makes interceſſion for us, and ſo he becomes our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, our ſanctification; and this Goſpel was witneſſed firſt by Chriſt himſelf; but ſince, ſaith the Apoſtles, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye reconciled to God; &amp; thoſe that were thus wrought upon, through their miniſtry, are ſaid to be the called of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Act.</hi> 28.23. and ſo is made good the words of <hi>Jude</hi> 3. contend earneſtly for that Faith which was ONCE delivered to the Saints.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>By this</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Lawſon) <hi>we ſet the Scriptures in the room of the Father, and Son, and ſo (ſaith he) deny both Father and Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Many are the ſhifts of men to race out of the World that eſteem of the Scriptures, which indeed is but due, being accounted by the Apoſtles HOLY Scriptures, in reſpect of their uſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2. whereby is made known the will of Chriſt, in which we walk in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring (through his grace) the honour of the Father, and Son; which cannot be a denying of the Father and Son; but he that hath his eyes cloſed will ſay ſo; it is ſaid, the Scripture is profitable for teaching, correction, and inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, and that there ought to be attendance given to the reading of it, yet moſt ſurely neither <hi>Paul</hi> that ſpoke it, nor <hi>Timothy</hi> to whom it was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, denyed either Father, or Son; nor pulled off the Crown from Chriſts head, putting it upon the Scriptures, as ſaith <hi>Lawſon</hi> we do; yet ſay no more than they did, he moſt ſurely is worthy of the Crown, that dyed to bring forth a word of ſalvation for men, and that ſtrengthens us by his Spirit to walk up accordingly; from whom the Apoſtles removed it not, yet ſaid to men, WE pray you in Chriſts STEAD, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. yea, and that from the Scriptures, perſwading men from morning till evening, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.23. <hi>Aaron</hi> was to hearken unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was to put words into his mouth, and therein to be unto him in STEAD of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.16. yet neither he nor the Apoſtles robbed God of his honour, he being the original; of him, and through him, and to him are all things, to whom be glory for ever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:117938:12"/>
            <p>Oh how great are the ſelf-exaltations of theſe men! how doth their arrogancy appear! while they ſo mightily indeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy mens faith of the Scriptures, as being adiſcovery of the Lords will, and yet in the mean while furniſh the Nations almoſt in every corner with THEIR SCRIPTURES (which is writings) calling them a DISCOVERY of ſeveral particulars, which they publiſh to men, as the will of the Lord; as witneſſeth <hi>Deusburys</hi> book, which he calls a diſcovery of mans return to his firſt eſtate; with a diſcovery of Myſtery <hi>Babylon. Martha Simmons</hi> alſo ſpeaks ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in diſcovery of the nakedneſſe of all profeſſions &amp;c. <hi>Farn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> alſo hath writ that the Truth might be cleared, and the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance both of Prieſt and people might be diſcovered. What! O friends, may men know from their writings, and yet not from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writings, which were written for that very end, that the CER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINTY of the Lords will might be known? <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.3, 4. and that men MIGHT beleeve, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31. God forbid.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Alſo I deny the Spirit</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Lawſon <hi>in his book</hi>) <hi>in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that by the Scriptures is made known or revealed the will of Christ; becauſe the Spirit ſearches all things, yea the deep things of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is indeed ſuch words ſpoken by <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.10. but <hi>Lawſon</hi> waiting ſo much upon the darkneſs within him, hath wreſted the Scripture, and ſo himſelf is found unlearned, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. though he hath talked ſo much of the tongue of the learned; for the Apoſtle in the words before, ſaith that eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, &amp;c. the things which God hath prepared for them that love him; but God (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit; that is, them things which God hath prepared for thoſe that love him; wherefore he ſaith <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. that we might know the things which are freely given to us of God; wherefore moſt plainly will it appear to him that ſearches, that the Apoſtle THERE ſpeaks not of the Spirits revealing the duty of man, but rather of the great glory, and reward, that is the portion of them that walk up in their duty; though it is not to be denyed, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther witneſſed by experienced ſouls, that the Spirit doth teach them, maniſeſting and laying open particularly the corruption of the heart; (which is but in general heads ſignified in Scripture) and not only ſo; but alſo mortifies the ſame, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. and alſo beareth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with our ſpirit, that we are the children of God, <hi>verſe</hi> 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo are we ſealed with the holy Spirit of promiſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117938:13"/>by the Spirit is revealed and clearly made known, thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars which are obſcurely ſignified in the Scripture, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.5, 6. which things, together with the revelations of the future glory, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man receives not, for they are fooliſhneſs unto him; wherefore he is required in the firſt place to repent, and be baptized for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, and then is he under the promiſe of the holy Spirit, <hi>Act,</hi> 2.38. through which he may diſcern theſe things, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit withall, but by reaſon of darkneſs it is not comprehended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt the true Light ſpeaks otherwiſe, ſaying, that the World CANNOT RECEIVE the Spirit; wherefore though the Spirit be a Teacher as aforeſaid, yet it is to be conſidered that the promiſe thereof, ſo as to dwell in men, is to ſuch as yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that ſelf-denying Doctrin of repentance, and are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thoſe ordinances that belong to penitent men; wherefore ſaith the Apoſtles, God hath given the Spirit to them that OBEY him, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.32. and thoſe that ſay God hath given him alſo to diſobedient men, as a dweller in them, doth make the Apoſtles words of no effect; if the Spirit dwel in every unbeleeving man, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Paul,</hi> when he asked the Diſciples whether they had received the Spirit SINCE they beleeved? moreover when they ſignified their ignorance, ſaying, we have not ſo much as heard whether there be any holy Spirit, <hi>Paul</hi> did not, as we find, tell them that they were miſtaken, ſhewing them that the Spirit was in them, but by reaſon of darkneſs they comprehended it not; but rather queſtions their faith, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.2, 3. ſhewing plainly that faith is to precede the receiving of the Spirit, as an indweller, wherefore ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> after ye beleeved, ye were ſealed with the holy Spirit of promiſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13. all which being conſidered, may ſhew us the Quakers miſ-underſtanding of <hi>Pauls</hi> words, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. who ſpeaking before unto the Church concerning the diverſities of the gifts of the Spirit, ſaid unto them (conſidered as a Church, ſuch as were ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Chriſt) that the end of the manifeſtation of the Spirit given to every man, was to profit withall, but him the World cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; <hi>John</hi> 14.17.</p>
            <p>Another ſhift of thoſe men, to put by the true intention of writing the Scriptures, is to tell people that they are not the Word of God; and their reaſon is, becauſe Chriſt is called the Word, which may not be denyed; but yet Chriſt is not ſo the Word, but that himſelf
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117938:13"/>teſtifies the Scriptures to be the Word of God; for ſaith he to the Phariſees; <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, honour thy Father and thy Mother; but ye ſuffer a man no more to do ought for his Father, or his Mother, and thus ye make the Word of God of no effect, <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.12, 13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.6. that is plainly, the Scriptures, which ſaith, honour thy Father; and thy Mother. God ſaid to <hi>Moſes</hi> that he would raiſe up a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that he would put his words into his mouth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.18. unto this, Chriſt bears record, ſaying, I ſpeak not of my ſelf, but the Father gave mee commandement what I ſhould ſpeak; now judge ye I pray whether any of Chriſts hearers might have ſaid, and well ſaid, that the words which he ſpake was not the Word of God; if they might not, then the Scriptures being a preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of what Chriſt did do, and teach, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.1. may properly be ſaid to be the Word of God; even ſo it appears <hi>Paul, Sylvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> underſtood it, who writing unto the Saints, teſtified that they had heard of them, and RECEIVED OF THEM how they ought to walk, yet they received it not as the word of men, but (as it is in Truth ſaith the Apoſtles) the Word of God, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.4.1. or the word of Truth, which <hi>Timothy</hi> was rightly to divide, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. but Chriſt is not divided; or a word of faith, becauſe it teſtifies of Righteouſneſs no otherwiſe attainable but by faith; yet not but that Chriſt is the author of Faith, he being that pure ſacrifice that makes reconciliation for ſins, through Faith in him; which the Scripture ſpeaks of; and ſo it ſtill remains, that through the Scriptures is made known the will of Chriſt, yea the CERTAINTY thereof, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.3, 4. it being evidently his will that his ſaying ſhould be ſet forth in writings as they are, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by ſeverall counſels, and cautions of Chriſt, the danger where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he well knew would not happen in the dayes of his then Diſciples, and ſo had been uſeleſſe, had he not intended that what he ſpake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them ſhould be recorded for the benefit of after generations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. wherefore diligently obſerve what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and give attendance to the reading thereof, and I beſeech you in the fear of the Lord, that ye ſlight them not, no not in the leaſt; leaſt the judgements of God break out upon you (I mean hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart to beleeve lyes) Oh remember how the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> when hee burnt the Scripture, that was ſent unto him, that hee might know the Lords will, and turn unto him, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 36.23.30, 31. whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117938:14"/>OUR LEARNING, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. let us learn, let us learn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker alſo denyeth that the Ministers of Chriſt (indued with the Spirit of Chriſt) ought to miniſter, or preach from the Scriptures; as appears in</hi> Lawſons <hi>book, called the</hi> untaught Teacher. <hi>pa.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p>Undoubtedly this will ſeem ſtrange, becauſe in their preaching, and alſo in their books they commonly ſpeak of Scripture; but friends, there lyes a winding Serpent in that graſs; for from it they ſpeak not, (though OF it) but from that which they call Light within them; which they wait upon, as their ONLY TEACH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER, the teachings of which they witneſs forth, and leaſt iniquity ſhould appear as iniquity nakedly, they pervert the plain Scriptures into myſterious meanings, and frames them up one way or other to that which their Light ſpeaks within them, and SO ſpeak much of the Scriptures; thus is it a MYSTERY OF INIQUITY; yea though it be altogether againſt the plain Scripture, yet will they follow the dictates of the darkneſs within them; and that herein I abuſe them not, I preſent unto you one revelation of their Teacher, that is concerning the Scripture, which teſtifies that a woman is not permitted to ſpeak in the Church by way of teaching, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in other caſes; by which (ſay they) is meant the wiſdome of the fleſh, either in man or woman, which revelation <hi>Farnworth</hi> thought worthy of the preſs, and ſo publiſhed it; yea I have been told by them, that that woman which is forbidden thus to ſpeak, was within mee, and ſpake in mee; this ſay they proceeds from the Light, but woe unto them that puts darkneſs for Light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>All that hath been already ſaid, ſerves for the proof of this, which by them is denyed; for the Light which they ſpeak of within being tryed, and found darkneſs, and the Scriptures that which makes known the will of Chriſt, it muſt neéds follow as a ſafe practice, for the ſpirituall man, to miniſter from the Scriptures, ſince we find it alſo agreeable with the practice of the Apoſtles, who at their firſt publick preaching after Chriſts aſcention directed the people to the Scriptures, yea a great part of that which <hi>Peter</hi> preached, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. conſiſted of repetitions of the Prophets words, which was to them, and is to us, in Scripture; yea as matter of proof of what he ſpoke; when he had aſſerted that Chriſt was riſen from the dead, he adds this reaſon, <hi>verſe</hi> 25. FOR <hi>DAVID</hi> SPEAKETH concerning him, &amp;c. yea very much Scripture doth he there relate, and then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117938:14"/>expounds them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29, 30, 31. and reaſons from them, <hi>verſe</hi> 34. and this became effectual, whereas if <hi>Peter</hi> had been altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtructed by a Teacher within him, and owned no other, than the ſame Teacher within, his hearers, muſt have been the only means to convince them of their ſins; but it is otherwiſe recorded, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. when they heard THIS (that is <hi>Peters</hi> preaching from the Scriptures) they were pricked in heart; and alſo the only thing through which they might be added to the Saints; but it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaid, even that they which gladly received HIS WORD were baptized, and the ſame day there was added unto them about three thouſand ſouls, <hi>verſe.</hi> 41. to this agrees alſo the manner of <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching. who having aſſerted the ſame Doctrin, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.33. proceeds on with this argument, IT IS WRITTEN, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king much uſe of the Scriptures of the Prophets, for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Doctrin which, he delivered, <hi>verſe</hi> 34, 35, 36. ſo alſo <hi>Apollos</hi> by his miniſtry mightily convinced the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſhewing BY THE SCRIPTURES, that Jeſus was Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.28 and this is noted of him as his worthy practice. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo when he was at <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> reaſoned with the people three Sabbath dayes OUT OF THE SCRIPTURES, opening, and alledging that Chriſt muſt needs have ſuffered, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.2, 3. and when he was at <hi>Rome,</hi> he perſwaded the people concerning Jeſus OUT OF THE LAW OF <hi>MOSES,</hi> AND OUT OF THE PROPHETS from morning till evening, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.23. through which many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, and they are happy (whatever others ſay of a Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as the only Teacher) for Chriſt hath prayed for them, <hi>Job.</hi> 17.20. I pray not for theſe alone, but for them alſo which ſhall beleeve on mee through THEIR WORD; wherefore the Quaker erres; not knowing the Scriptures, when he affirms that the only means of Faith, is the immediate teachings of Chriſt dwelling within men, for the Scripture teſtifies that the Goſpel at the FIRST was ſpoken by the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. which ſaying the Quaker makes of no effect, by his ſaying that Chriſt firſt, laſt, and ſo alwayes by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; in men, preaches it.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If it be objected, and ſaid that many things, which the Apostles preached could not be proved by the Scriptures of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and the Prophets, they in the leaſt not ſpeaking of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer to him or them whoſe objection ſoever it is, that particularly indeed ſome things was not ſpoken of in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before them, which they preached; but moſt plain it is, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117938:15"/>ſuch things they delivered from what Chriſt perſonally had bee fore commanded them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I HAVE commanded you; which things are written that the certainty thereof MIGHT BE KNOWN, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1, 3, 4 and ſo in preaching from it, wee do no more than what the Apoſtles were commanded to do; which things, though not particularly ſpoken of in thoſe Scriptures before them, yet therm generally included, for when the Apoſtles had proved, and convinced men that Jeſus was the Chriſt, the Prophet which the Scriptures of <hi>Moſes</hi> fore-told of, by the ſame Scriptures they were required to hear him (that is Chriſt) in all things whatſoever hee ſhould ſay unto them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.18.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>By this</hi> Tho. Lawſon <hi>ſaith, we ſhut out our ſelves from the holy men of old, who were Miniſters of the New Teſtament, of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and not of the Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Many are the ſhifts of theſe men, to make voyd the true uſe of the Scriptures, yet the waking eye will ſee, and that clearly, that the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of the Letter of the Law, which both then, and now conſidered alone, killeth, for in the next verſe he calls it the Miniſtration of Death, written, and engraven in ſtones, which all may eaſily know was the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by which no fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh ſhall be juſtified, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7. of this Letter the Apoſtles were not Miniſters of, neither are we; but even this the Apoſtles ſlighted not in the leaſt, becauſe men ſpoke of it from the Letter, for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves miniſtred forth the ſayings of the Prophets, which alſo was in Letter, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.28. &amp; 28.23. but becauſe it teſtified of death to ſinners (which all were, and now are in their firſt condition) and of no remiſſion of ſins, which the New Teſtament doth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith, we are able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit, which teſtament (as it is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred forth) teſtifies that men may receive the Spirit, through ſubmiſſion to the law of Faith; to which agrees the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> he THAT MINISTRETH TO YOV THE SPIRIT, doth he it by the Works of the Law, or by the hearing of Faith? <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.5. and ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> Repent, and be baptiſed, and yee ſhall receive the Spirit; who alſo prayed, and layed on his hands upon the baptiſed <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that they might receive the Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.15.17. this appears alſo ſo to be, from that which the Apoſtle oppoſeth it unto, even the Law, the miniſtration of Death; (which is) that which teſtified of Death; ſo contrariwiſe, the miniſtration of the Spirit is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117938:15"/>that which teſtifies of the Spirit, as receiveable in the way aforeſaid; wherefore the Servants of Chriſt miniſtring from, or out of the Scriptures, through his Spirit, are not ſhut out from the holy men of old, for they alſo miniſtred out of the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.23. and ſhewed by the Scriptures that Jeſus was the Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.28. yet were they not miniſters of the Letter; yea their common Language in their Miniſtry was, FOR IT IS WRITTEN, FOR IT IS WRITTEN; but hee that hath another ſpirit ſaith, THE LIGHT WITHIN, THE LIGHT WITHIN, yea as the only teacher.</p>
            <p>Herein is <hi>Lawſon</hi> found to be unlearned, having wreſted the Scriptures, though he hath ſpoke much of the tongue of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his Book againſt me; the occaſion of which I here ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto you. At a certain time <hi>Tho. Lawſon</hi> demanded of mee what the tongue of the Learned was? according to that ſaying, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.4. now I knowing the ſnatching, and catching nature of theſe men, deſired him to ſignifie the meaning of his Queſtion in other words; which was, as he ſaid, What the ſervants of Chriſt are to miniſter from? and ſo, ſaid he, What is it that thou miniſters from? Your Queſtion, ſaid I, ſhall be preſently anſwered, and as for the former expreſſions we will paſs by, ſince you ſay that this is your intention therein; for I am not ſatisfied concerning the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prophet in that place; and ſo immediatly both Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and Anſwer was written. <hi>(Q.)</hi> What it was that I mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred from? <hi>(Anſ.)</hi> I miniſter from the Scriptures, through the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God, yet notwithſtanding hath he from this made a great out-cry of my unlearnedneſs, entitling a Book thence, therein informing men that I told him, that I knew not what the tongue of the learned was; but how farre his information ſavours of ſincerity, and how well it becomes him that ſo mightily pleads for perfection, I leave it to the wiſe to judge; remembring this ſaying, what do theſe FEEBLE JEWS? <hi>Nehem,</hi> 4.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker affirmeth that the Law without man, that is, the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Law, doth not convince men of ſin, but Chriſt the light dwelling in the godly, and ungodly,</hi> Lawſ. Book, p. 15.</p>
            <p>That which hath been already ſaid, ſerves alſo to manifeſt the errour of this Principle, for the Scriptures being written, that the CERTAINTY of the Lords Will might bee known, which was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117938:16"/>moſt ſurely beleeved by the Saints of old, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.1, 3, 4. muſt needs alſo certainly give us to know when we walk contrary thereunto; yea in plain words ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> the Scripture is profitable for REPROOF and CORRECTION, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. and <hi>Apollos</hi> ſhewing by the Scriptures that Jeſus was Chriſt, is ſaid MIGHT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY TO CONVINCE the <hi>Jews;</hi> to which agrees <hi>Pauls</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to <hi>Timothy</hi> about Biſhops, ſignifying therein that he muſt be one, able by SOUND DOCTRIN, both to exhort and CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINCE the gainſayers, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1.9. according to which agrees the relation of the people dwelling at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Act. 2.37. WHEN THEY HEARD THIS (to with, <hi>Peters</hi> powerfull preaching by the Spirit out of the Scriptures) they were pricked at the heart; thus was he a ſower that went forth, and went OUT to ſow good ſeed into the hearts of men, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.5. but according to the ſenſe of the Quaker, the ſower dwels in the ground (the wicked world) oh horrible confuſion! but it may be the Quaker will take ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, becauſe it is ſaid a ſower, and not ſowers; but the wiſe will conſider that there is no room in the leaſt for an advantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt what here, or elſewhere hath been ſaid, for by the parable of one loſt ſheep, or one loſt peece of ſilver; Chriſt juſtifies his practice in companying with many Publicans, and ſinners, <hi>Luk</hi> 15.1, 2, 4, 8; therefore it follows not that Chriſt himſelf in men is the ſower only, though all is from him originally, for the Apoſtles ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. WE have ſown unto you ſpiritual things; which they did in Chriſts STEAD, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Chriſt ſaith when the Spirit is come he ſhall reprove the World of ſin, of Righteouſneſſe, and of judgement,</hi> Joh. 16.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is to bee obſerved that hee doth not ſay, when hee is come, in the World, but having before, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. ſhewed the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diency of his going away, ſaid, if I depart, I will ſend him unto YOU, that was his Diſciples, and when he is come, (that is to you, for the World ſaith Chriſt CANNOT RECEIVE HIM, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.17.) he ſhall reprove the World of ſin; by which Spirit, when the Diſciples had received it, they went forth with all boldneſſe, and utterance, plainly declaring the word of Truth, perſwading men OUT OF THE LAW OF <hi>MOSES,</hi> AND OUT OF THE PROPHETS (which was in Scripture) from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning till evening, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.23. with ſuch power, and wiſdome, as that the adverſaries were not able to reſiſt the Spirit by which THEY ſpake, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.10. wherefore (notwithſtanding this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117938:16"/>I have not ſo learned Chriſt, as to beleeve that the wicked hath this Spirit of promiſe dwelling in them, when as Chriſt ſaith, they CANNOT receive it; what God may do by his Spirit for men, at certain times, eſpecially where other means are wanting, I here ſpeak not againſt; but againſt this conception of theirs, <hi>viz.</hi> that the holy Spirit of God DWELS in all UNHOLY perſons of the World, as that which alone convinceth them of ſin, and of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Moreover ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 3.20. by the Law is the KNOW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEDGE OF SIN, yea that Law by the deeds of which no fleſh ſhall be juſtified; whereby the Apoſtle prevents the Quakers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection concerning his ſpirituall Law, by which alone he ſaies men ſhall be juſtified; and alſo ſaith <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. that he had not known ſin, but by the Law, for, ſaith he, I had not known luſt, except the Law had ſaid, thou ſhalt not covet, which Law he ſaith, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. they then were delivered from, and <hi>verſe</hi> 4. dead to; <hi>James</hi> alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Spirit told the Saints, that in caſe they had reſpect to perſons, they would be by the Law (the tenor of which was, thou ſhalt not commit adultery, thou ſhalt not kill) CONVINCED as tranſgreſſors, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11. yet ſaith <hi>Lawſon,</hi> the outward Law doth not convince man of ſin, and his reaſon is, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid that he was once alive without the Law; not conſidering that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in their childiſh and youthfull dayes which are vanity, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.10. may properly be ſaid to bee without the Law (though nurtured by them that have the Law) whike they live in luſts, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting after every pleaſant object of the eye; not underſtanding the things of God; but when the commandement comes to their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, capable to comprehend ſuch things, then ſin is revived, and they dye, and ſo remains, till remiſſion of ſin is aſſured to them; now in reference to thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> that have not the written Law, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that they HAVING NOT THE LAW (marke that) are a Law unto themſelves, (which never was ſaid to them, or of them that had the written Law;) that is concerning ſuch things as is held forth in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which ſaith, the man that doth thoſe things ſhall live by then, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5. but the things relating to Faith in Chriſt we find was made known UNTO men by outward diſcoveries but ſomething to this hath been already ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaith that the Scriptures are not a touchſtone to try Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits withall, as ſaith</hi> Lawſon <hi>in his book, pa.</hi> 14.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:117938:17"/>
            <p>The ſumme of all concerning the Quakers eſteem of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is thus, THEY OWN IT NOT A RULE, WHERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BY THE WILL OF CHRIST MAY BE KNOWN; NEITHER THAT WHICH SAINTS (endued with the Spirit) ARE TO PREACH FROM; NEITHER THAT WHICH CONVINCETH OF SIN; NEITHER THE TOUCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STONE TO TRY SPIRITS WITHALL; yet will they ſay that they own all the Scriptures from the beginning of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> unto the end of the <hi>Revelations</hi> (but oh their ſhamefull deceit!)</p>
            <p>Now this laſt particular muſt needs be found ſhort of truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scriptures are found to be the rule; now that which is the rule, muſt needs be the tryer, or touchſtone to manifeſt unruly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, though it be true that there is a gift of the Spirit, which diſcerns the unſound man, yea by very ſlender appearances, yet hereby is he not ſo to bee tryed, as to be openly publiſhed, and judged, till ſome evident diſobedience to the written Law, and ſo by their fruits we muſt know them, not he that ſaith Lord, Lord, or Light, Light, ſhall enter into the Kingdome, but he that doth the will of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; whoſe will is ſignified in the Scripture; moreover when Chriſt had informed his Diſciples of falſe Prophets, and falſe Chriſts, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their works, and ſayings which ſhould come, hee ſaid unto them, take heed, behold, I have FORETOLD YOU ALL THINGS, <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.23. ye that fear God conſider, how inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable we ſhall be found if (when Chriſt hath ſo expreſt his kindneſſe in foretelling the danger, and preſcribing the manner of its appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that we might eſcape it) it, I ſay we ſhall not take heed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, comparing the workings, and ſayings of men with this written Prophecy, and ſo try the Spirits thereby; have we not good ground to beleeve that theſe men are evilly diſpoſed, in that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to come to the rule to be tryed? what, is not that to try men withall now, which Chriſt will judge and try, and judge men by in the laſt day? the word that I have ſpoken (ſaith Chriſt) ſhall judge him in the laſt day, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.48. which word is witneſſed to us in the Scripture; but <hi>Lawſon</hi> ſuppoſes this day to be now, which is to try every mans work, wherein the righteous is to be diſcerned from the wicked, according to that <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17, 18.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſaith hee) not the Scriptures; but alaſs, the more he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to avoid the tryal thereby, the more thereby he is manifeſted; for by this he is found unlearned, though he hath ſo much ſpoken
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117938:17"/>of the tongue of the learned, by wreſting the Scriptures; for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet there ſpeaks of a day, wherein all that are proud, and all that DO wickedly ſhall be deſtroyed, leaving neither root, nor branch, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1. which the opened eyes ſees clearly is not now; of which day <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, in that place inſtanced by <hi>Lawſon,</hi> wherefore he ſaith, the day SHALL declare it, from whence theſe men conclude, that that day then did, and now doth; but <hi>Paul</hi> had the Spirit of Truth; whom we find (even as a dying man) expecting a Crown of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which (ſaith he) the Lord SHALL give mee at THAT DAY, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6, 8. wherefore let us prize the Law, and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, to which if men ſpeak not according, it is becauſe they have no Light in them; though they may ſpeak much of Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaith, that Chriſt is already come the Second time, and</hi> George Fox <hi>affirmed in plain words, before many witneſſes, that hee knew him come within him, and he looked for him to come NO OTHER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WISE; and</hi> James Parnel <hi>affirmeth: that they that confeſs not Chriſt come in THEIR fleſh, are the Antichrist, and alſo affirmeth, that by preaching of a Chriſt in heaven, the Devil gets his work done on earth; as appears in his Book called,</hi> Satans Deſign diſcovered, p. 19.25.</p>
            <p>This being well conſidered, is the ready way to fulfill that which is written concerning thoſe that ſhall come, ſaying, I am Chriſt, deceiving many, before the comming of Chriſt indeed, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be till firſt the true Faith of his comming be made void, which theſe men indeavour to do; by ſaying that the comming of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which Chriſt ſaid he would ſend, was that ſecond comming of Chriſt, which the Scripture ſo much ſpeaks of; but evidently it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears otherwiſe, becauſe the Spirit by Chriſt is called ANOTHER COMFORTER, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. which ſaith, he will not come ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I go away, but if I depart, I will ſend him unto you, <hi>John</hi> 16. 7. plainly ſhewing, that the Spiritis the comforter of the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in Chriſts perſonal abſence; for when Chriſt ſpake of his own comming, he ſaid on this wiſe, I will come again, yea as the SON OF MAN, <hi>Matth</hi> 24.37. <hi>John</hi> 14.3. but ſpeaking of the Spirit, ſaies, I will ſend HIM unto you; which when the Apoſtles had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, they went forth teſtifying the Lord Jeſus, not come within them, but as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, whom the HEAVEN muſt reveive, till the times of reſtitution of all things. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. yet at this time had <hi>Peter</hi> the Spirit; but leſt there ſhould be room for the Quakers to ſay
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117938:18"/>that that Heaven was within them; conſider alſo the relation of <hi>Stephen,</hi> who ſtedfaſtly looking UP into Heaven, ſaw the HEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VENS OPENED, and the SON OF MAN, ſtanding on the right hand of God, yet was he FILLED with the Spirit; but his wiſdome was to diſtinguiſh between him ſent, and the ſender; and in this Faith he DYED; and a long ſeaſon afterwards we find <hi>Peter</hi> remaining the ſame; confidently affirming that Chriſt was gone into Heaven, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.22. ſignifying to the Elders, that when the chief Shepheard SHALL APPEAR, ye (ſaith he) ſhall receive a Crown of glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. to which agrees the Faith of <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> alſo, who looked for the Saviour Chriſt FROM HEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. what from the fleſhly hearts of men? judge ye that are wiſe; theſe alſo at that time had the Spirit; to which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees alſo the Faith of the Apoſtle <hi>John.</hi> who ſaid, when he SHALL appear, we ſhall be like him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. yet then it was the Spirit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto him; the Church of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> was of the ſame Faith, waiting for Chriſt FROM HEAVEN, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. yet then were they the Elect of God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. the <hi>Corinthians</hi> alſo being inriched by him in all utterance, and in all knowledge, comming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in no gift, yet were waiting for the comming of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5, 7. the Church of <hi>Thiatyra</hi> was to hold faſt, that which they already had, till he come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25. judge nothing before the time, untill the Lord come, 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 4.5. yet ſaith <hi>Thomas Laucock,</hi> where is the promiſe of his comming? is he aſleep? but <hi>Peter</hi> tells ſuch ſcoffers, that the Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe, but is long-ſuffering towards men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not willing that any ſhould periſh, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. wherefore be patient UNTO THE COMMING of the Lord, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.7. for this is the true Grace wherein we ſtand, even that which brings ſalvation; for (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) the Grace of God, that bringeth ſalvation, teacheth us to live godil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in this world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to LOOK FOR the glorious appearing of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Saints waiting for the comming of Chriſt, was but for a greater meaſure of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which is ſpoken elſewhere concerning their denyal of the Lord Jeſus, will ſhew the emptineſs of this objection: yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, Chriſt was not taken up into Heaven by meaſures, and at times; but while he bleſſed them, he was parted from them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.51. and he ſhall SO COME IN LIKE MANNER as the Diſciples did SEE him go into Heaven, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11. wherefore the uſual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117938:18"/>in Scripture is, the COMMING, not COMMINGS of Chriſt; where it is ſpoken of him, ſince his aſcenſion; wherefore ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to the Saints, be ye not ſoon ſhaken in mind, or troubled, neither by Spirit, nor by Word, nor by Letter, as from us, as that the day of Chriſt is at hand, for that day ſhall not come, except there be a falling away firſt, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2, 3. yet ſaith the Quaker, it was in a great meaſure come, but thereby he is found to be led by that Spirit, which then troubled the Saints, pretending the day of Chriſt to be, before it was to be, which <hi>Paul</hi> afterwards calls a myſtery of iniquity then working, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. by this alſo he makes void the uſe of Chriſts parables, concerning his comming, which himſelf ſets out by a man taking a far journey, giving authority to his ſervants, <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.34. who after a long time commeth, and reckoneth with them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.19. in what manner he is capable to come, judge ye, and remember that Chriſt ſaith HE IS AS A MAN, as aboveſaid (that is in reſpect of his ſuddain comming at a time;) wherefore he ſaith, watch, and pray, for ye know not when the TIME is; <hi>Mar.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3.33. moreover conſider that <hi>Peter,</hi> even when hee was ready to DYE, witneſſed not the day of the Lord come, but ſaith, the day of the Lord WILL <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>OME, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. &amp; 1.14. in like manner <hi>Paul</hi> when he was r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ady to DYE, ſaid that there was laid UP for him a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which (ſaith he) the Lord SHALL give mee at THAT DAY, and not only to mee; but unto all that love his app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aring, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 4.6, 8. and the holy men of old dyed in the faith, NOT HAVING RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEIVED THE PROMISES, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.</p>
            <p>Another way I take notice of, whereby faith in the true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt is indeavoured to be (at preſent) made void; and that is by perverting the ſignes of his comming into myſteries, and ſo ſcrues them to be ſignes fulfilled in them, before their conceived comming of Chriſt; but unto you that fear the Lord, this</p>
            <p>I ſay, that there is a good ground for us now to beleeve that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and perplexity of Nations; the Sea, and waves roaring, mens hearts ſailing them for fear, the powers of Heaven being ſhaken, are ſignes of Chriſts comming; as there was for the Saints of old to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that <hi>Sion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> King, even the Lord Jeſus, ſhould come riding upon an Aſſe, and a Colt the ſole of an Aſſe, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.9. which even ſo was fulfilled, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.4, 5.</p>
            <p>And alſo as good ground for us now to beleeve, that as the lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhineth out of the Eaſt, even unto the Weſt, SO the comming
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117938:19"/>of the ſon of man ſhall be; as there was for the people of God in the dayes of old to beleeve, that the Chriſt which was to come, ſhould be prized at thirty peeces of ſilver; with which ſhould be bought the Potters field, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.12, 13. which even ſo came to paſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.3, 7, 9.</p>
            <p>Alſo as good ground for us now to beleeve, that there ſhall ariſe many falſe Chriſts, ſaying, I am Chriſt, ſhewing great ſignes and wonders, before the comming of Chriſt, as ſignes of his comming; as there was for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to beleeve, that the Chriſt was to be numbred with tranſgreſſors, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53.12. which even ſo came to paſs, <hi>Mark</hi> 15.28.</p>
            <p>There is alſo as good ground for us to beleeve, that the Sun and Moon ſhall be darkned before the coming of Chriſt, as ſigns of his coming; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had to beleeve, that a Virgin ſhould bear a Son, whoſe name ſhould be <hi>Immanuel,</hi> that is, God with us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14. which even ſo alſo came to paſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.22, 23.</p>
            <p>As good ground alſo there is for us now to beleeve that the Stars ſhall fall from Heaven, before the coming of Chriſt; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had to beleeve that there was a time to come, wherein a voyce of lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and bitter weeping in <hi>Ramah</hi> ſhould be heard, <hi>Rachel</hi> weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for her Children, &amp;c. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.15. which you know came ſo to paſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.17, 18.</p>
            <p>As good ground alſo there is for us now to beleeve, that Chriſt ſhall come in the Clouds of Heaven; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had, to beleeve that the Prophetical words of <hi>David</hi> ſhould be literally fulfilled (<hi>viz.</hi> in my thirſt they gave me vinegar to drink, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.21) as evidently they were, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.48.</p>
            <p>O remember the myſtery of iniquity, leaſt you daſh your ſelves in peeces againſt that rock; for, conſider, would Chriſt, yea when he made it his work to preſcribe the future dangers, that the Saints ſhould not be deceived, would he, I ſay, then deliver theſe many Signs, as he did, and intend that they ſhould bee myſteriouſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and not in the leaſt ſignifie it, judge yee that are judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and conſider how this opinion of Chriſts coming only in men croſſes the Scriptures, for when Chriſt comes, he comes in glory, WITH his Angels, and WITH ten thouſand of his Saints, <hi>Jud.</hi> 14. And the Lord my God (ſaith the Prophet) ſhall come, and all the Saints WITH thee, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.5. (they being firſt caught up to meet the Lord in the air, and ſo ſhal EVER BE WITH THE LORD, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. BEFORE whom ſhall be GATHERED
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117938:19"/>all nations, and hee <hi>(AS A SHEPHEARD)</hi> ſhall divide one from another, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31, 32. Moreover, then Saints ſhall bee free from death, from ſorrow, from tears, yea from all manner of pain ſaith the Lord, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.4. yea Saints vile bodies ſhall then be made like unto the glorious body of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.21. and they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and as the Stars for ever and ever, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. yet ſaith <hi>Fox,</hi> Chriſt is come, and he looks for him to come no otherwiſe, but how, where, and in whom do theſe things appear? O the nakedneſs of this Dream! Moreover, when he comes, he ſhall rebuke ſtrong Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and they ſhall bear their Swords into Plow ſhares, and their Spears into Pruning-hooks; Nation ſhall not lift up ſword againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learn Warre any more, <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.3. yea he maketh Wars to ceaſe unto the end of the earth, <hi>Pſal</hi> 46 9. But doth this (O Friends) appear? and not rather Nation againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Kingdom againſt Kingdom, even as Chriſt foretold ſhould come; wherefore he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Saints are the Temple of God, and God dwels in them; and know you not that Chriſt is in you, except yee be reprobates; and Chriſt is in you the hope of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Moſt true it is that Saints are the Temple of God, and God doth now as well as heretofore dwell in his people; but <hi>Paul</hi> that ſpake theſe words, alſo ſaith, that Saints are an habitation of God <hi>THROVGH THE SPIRIT,</hi> Epheſ. 2.22. which (ſaith he) yee have OF God, and your Body is the Temple of the holy Spirit. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. And know yee not that yee are the Temple of God, and that the SPIRIT OF GOD dwelleth in you? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. yet we finde that theſe WAITED FOR THE COMING of the Lord Jeſus, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7. and unto that very Church unto which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, (Chriſt in you the hope of glory) He alſo ſaith, When Chriſt who is our life SHALL APPEAR, then ſhall we appear with him in glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. even when the Lord Jeſus SHALL be revealed FROM HEAVEN, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Stephen</hi> (though filled with the Spirit) yet teſtified to death, that he, looking UP into Heaven, ſaw Jeſus ſtanding on the right hand of God; yet if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. which (ſaith Chriſt) will not come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you except I GO AWAY, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7. which Spirit the Saints receiving, did not declare him to bee their only inheritance, but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117938:20"/>(ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) the EARNEST of our inheritance, UNTIL the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the purchaſed poſſeſſion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14. Chriſt dwelt in them by faith, the hope of glory; he ſaith not as the poſſeſſion of glory: yet ſaith the Quaker, Chriſt is come already in their fleſh, and hath given them eternal life in poſſeſſion; and is not afraid to ſay, that by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of a Chriſt in Heaven, the Devil gets his work done on earth, though a Cloud of Witneſſes, from the Saints of old, that witneſſeth their faith in Chriſt, that was in Heaven; yet did they the work of the Lord, oppoſing the Antichriſtian ſpirits; though the Quaker, to the great abuſe of the Scriptures, ſay, that ſuch are the Antichriſts that cannot confeſs Chriſt come in THEIR fleſh; (but of this you ſhall hear in the next particular.)</p>
            <p>The men of God ſaid, that Chriſt Jeſus ſhall SO COME as yee have ſeen him go into Heaven; the Quaker ſaith, not SO, but let us (with <hi>John</hi>) ſay, even SO COME LORD JESUS. But that which is written muſt firſt be accompliſhed, even the revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Man of ſin, the Son of perdition, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3, 4. the vile perſon which <hi>Daniel</hi> Propheſied of, ſucceeding the raiſer of Taxes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.20, 21. who ſhall do according to HIS WILL (the light within he ſaies) and ſhall exalt himſelf, and magnifie himſelf above every God, and ſhall ſpeak marvellous things againſt the GOD OF GODS; neither ſhall he REGARD THE GOD OF HIS FATHERS (who witneſſed their God to bee in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) but tells us of a God within their fleſh, ſo as to expect his coming NO OTHERWISE; wherefore ſaith <hi>Daniel,</hi> he ſhall acknowledge a STRANGE GOD, <hi>verſ.</hi> 36, 37, 39. by whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection he ſhall make Warre with the Saints, and ſhall prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; UNTILL the ancient of days come, and the time when the Saints ſhall poſſeſs the Kingdom, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.20, 21, 22. hee ſhall indeed THINK to change Times, and Laws, but the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall ſit (though he ſay it bee paſt to him) and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Dominion, and the greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven ſhall be given to the Saints; wherefore comfort one another with theſe words, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25, 26, 27. for though for a ſeaſon we may be ſlighted by reaſon of him, whoſe looks (<hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith) is more STOVT THAN HIS FELLOWS, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.20. and though GREAT WORDS may bee ſpoken againſt the moſt High, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. who is our God, whom we witneſs to be in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as the holy men of old did; yet he ſhall deſcend from Heaven to our joy, and in that day this ſhall bee ſaid, LO, THIS IS
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117938:20"/>OVR GOD; we have waited for him, and he will ſave us <hi>THIS IS THE LORD,</hi> we have waited for him; we will bee glad and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in HIS SALVATION, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9. but of this Salvation the fooliſh Virgins comes ſhort of, as well as the Antichriſt; wherefore in the fear of the Lord, our God, <hi>BE ZEALOVS, WATCH AND PRAY WITH FASTING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark I pray you, the foundation that is already laid, for the myſtery of this iniquity to work upon; (I mean their ſaying that Chriſt is come, and their looking for him no otherwiſe to come) for the Scripture ſaith, when Chriſt comes, he will command his Angels, to gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.40, 41. then alſo the Nations is to be ruled with a Rod of Iron, and ſhall be broken like a Potters veſſel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25, 26, 27. Chriſt revealing himſelf from heaven, in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7, 8. we (ſaith the Quaker) are the only Miniſters of God; and they are ſaid to be made a flame of fire, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7. and (ſay they) Chriſt is now revealed in us, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; what then ſhould hinder them (who are ſo apt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Scriptures) in time, to bee perſwaded in flaming fire, to take vengeance on them that know not God, in their ſenſe, and that offend in their ſenſe; and pretend it to be Chriſt in them, the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire taking vengeance according to the Scriptures; but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Quaker will ſay at preſent, as <hi>Hazael</hi> did, What, am I a Dogge, that I ſhould do this great thing? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.13. yet it may be the iſſue like that of <hi>Hazael;</hi> however (O Friends) let not things preſent, nor things to come ſeparate us from the love of God which hath abounded to us in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaith, that the Offering of Christs Body to be broken, and his Bloud to be ſhed, avails not, ſo as (through faith therein) to ſet free from ſin; but bloud in a Myſtery, and a body in a Myſtery, which we know not what it is, ſaith</hi> Lawſon <hi>in his Book,</hi> p. 18. <hi>which was typified by the fleſhly body of Chriſt, and his Bloud; and ſo in them is fulfilled the Propheſie of</hi> Peter, <hi>who foretold the bringing in of damnable Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, even DENYING THE LORD THAT BOVGHT THEM, which they must needs do, that affirm Chriſt is already come the ſecond time; and LOOKS for him to come NO OTHERWISE, whom (they ſay) NEVER DIED.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that is written muſt be fulfilled, therefore this may not ſeem ſtrange, nor indeed thoſe many DOVBLE-MEANING expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117938:21"/>that we meet withall, as coverts to hide the nakedneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> they ſhall PRIVILY bring in this damnable Hereſie, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. therefore though <hi>John</hi> ſpeak of a people that denieth both Father, and Son, yet that they ſhould not pretend both, is altogether incredible; conſidering that Sathan transforms himſelf to be (as it were) an Angel of <hi>LIGHT,</hi> wherefore it is ſaid to be a <hi>MYSTERY</hi> of iniquity; Oh then how ſhould we labour to be enriched with heavenly wiſdom? for the hour is a coming, and now is, wherein we muſt wraſtle againſt Principalities and the Powers of the darkneſs of this World; and who is ſufficient for theſe things? ſurely they, and they only that are not aſhamed of the Lord Jeſus, and his words, without whom we can do nothing, whom the Quaker knows not, owns not, for God hath ſent him the ſtrong deluſion that he ſhould beleeve a lye.</p>
            <p>Wherefore hee ſaith boldly, but blaſphemouſly, that the Lord Jeſus whom we profeſs is accurſed, profeſſing a ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit within him, to be the only Chriſt, which he ſuppoſes was in the fleſhly Body of Chriſt, and there ſuffered reproaches, revilings, and the like, and is (ſaith <hi>Parnel</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In his Shield of Truth, p 34.</note>) NOW manifeſted in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh, to condemn ſin in the fleſh, yea and that (ſaith <hi>Nayler</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In Satans deſign diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, p. 25.</note>) by his own ſufferings with them, in them; but <hi>Paul</hi> being of another ſpirit, ſpeaks of the fleſhly Body of Chriſt, in that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. which was indeed the likeneſs of (but not) ſinful fleſh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15. and not in the leaſt of the ſinful fleſh of men, ſo as to bear away ſin by his ſuffering in their bodies; for ſaith the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf bare our ſins in his <hi>OWN BODY</hi> on the Tree, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. and by this <hi>ONE OFFERING</hi> he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14 having made thereby a way for ſuch to enter boldly into the holieſt, even by his <hi>BLOVD,</hi> through the vail, that is to ſay, <hi>HIS FLESH, verſ.</hi> 19. 20 according to which the Apoſtle ſaith, he hath made peace through the bloud of his Croſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. and you hath hee reconciled in the <hi>BODY OF HIS FLESH, THROVGH DEATH, verſ.</hi> 22. not fleſh and bloud as Types, for my Fleſh is meat INDEED (ſaith Chriſt) and my Bloud drink INDEED; which he gave for the life of the World, himſelf being the ſubſtance of thoſe many types of the Law; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the bodies of thoſe Beaſts, whoſe bloud was brought into the Sanctuary for ſin, being burnt without the Camp, Jeſus alſo, that he might ſanctifie the people, with his own bloud, ſuffered without
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117938:21"/>the Gate, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.11, 12. according to which, ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> yee were redeemed with the precious bloud of Chriſt, as of a LAMBE without blemiſh, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. and without SHEDDING of bloud is no remiſſion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. even the bloud of his CROSS, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. now conſider I pray you, whether he be not of that numb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r which counts the bloud of the Covenant an <hi>UN HOLY THING,</hi> that ſhall deny the effect of this bloud, and tells us of bloud in a myſtery? Oh remember that iniquity appears in a myſtery; for what is there required of us by the Lord, that may not, upon this account, be made voyd at mans pleaſure, though never ſo plain? Did the Apoſtles preach up Juſtification by the Bloud of Chriſt, and yet is Juſtification by another thing, which they in the leaſt ſpeak not of? God forbid; moreover, how full are the Scriptures of expreſſions that ſignifies to us reconciliation by the death of Chriſt, yea the death of the <hi>CROSS, Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 2.8. yet even this alſo is perverted into a myſtery by theſe men who imagines that Chriſt never dyed; but this Serpent lyeth hid in the Graſs, and is not eaſily to be ſeen, but the Graſs withereth, and the Man of Sin ſhall be revealed the Son of perdition; and this myſtery ſprings from an opinion that the ſpirit ſuffering within that Perſon of Jeſus, was the Chriſt, and ſo readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you ſhall hear them ſay, that they own him, who witneſſed a good confeſſion before <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> meaning the ſpirit within him. Moreover they will ſay, that they own him, who ſuffered upon Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> meaning the ſpirit within him; which ſpirit they ſay, is now within their bodies of fleſh; now judge yee, how fair a foundation hereby is laid for thoſe ſayings to bee built upon, which was foretold ſhould be ſaid by many that ſhould ariſe, ſaying, I AM CHRIST; which muſt be before the end, which when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it is, let us remember that the Chriſt indeed hath charged us, ſaying <hi>BELEEVE THEM NOT.</hi> Now that the fleſhly Body of Chriſt, as it was by him offered up to death, even the death of the Croſs, relates to the ſalvation of the Beleever, as effected through that, is further evident, becauſe the Apoſtles (who well knew what Chriſt was) teſtified to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they had by wicked hands crucified, and ſlain the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23. and betrayed, and murthered the juſt one, ſaith <hi>Stephen,</hi> Acts 7.52. whom they ſlew, and hanged on a tree, ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 10.39. and this was charged upon them for their wicked act towards the perſon of Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> without them (and not for murthering of Chriſt within them, as it is very likely the deceived ſoul would have it) becauſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117938:22"/>the Apoſtle in his charge, declares that when they had fulfilled all that was written of him, they took him (whom they had ſlain) <hi>DOWN FROM THE TREE,</hi> and laid him in a <hi>SEPVLCHRE, Act.</hi> 13.28, 29. whom God raiſed, with whom the Apoſtles ate, and drank after his reſurrection, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.41. even him whom the <hi>Jews</hi> ſlew, and hanged on a tree, <hi>verſe</hi> 39.</p>
            <p>Now we cannot but know, that it was a fleſhly, ſubſtantiall body of Chriſt, that they ſlew, murthered, and crucified upon the tree, and in ſo doing, the Apoſtles unanimouſly affirm that they ſlew Jeſus, (which in Engliſh is SAVIOUR) and yet doth hee not, through it, ſave? God forbid that we ſhould thus deny the Lord that bought us; for HE that the <hi>Jews</hi> thus ſlew, and hanged on a tree, with whom the Apoſtles ate, and drank after hee roſe from the dead, HE (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi>) commanded us to preach, and to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that it is HE (marke) which was ordained of God to bee the Judge of quick, and dead; and to HIM, ſaith <hi>Peter;</hi> give all the Prophets witneſſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.39, 41, 42, 43. yea the Angel of God deſcending from Heaven, bears witneſſe to this truth, who ſaid to the holy women, that came to the Sepulchre; Jeſus (that is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour) is not here, he is riſen, behold the place where they laid HIM, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.6. where the LORD LAY, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.6. yet will the Quaker ſlight this body, but thereby he is found to have a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Spirit, from that which the Apoſtles had, and ſo a falſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for they handling this body with their hands, in the relation thereof, ſaid, that which we have ſeen with our eyes, and looked upon, and our hands have handled of the Word of life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.1. and ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> God hath made that SAME JESUS, whom yee have crucified both LORD AND CHRIST, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36. and the Quaker denying this, is Antichriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for he that confeſſeth not Jeſus Chriſt come in the fleſh is Antichriſt, ſaith <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.3. now by what hath been ſaid, tis evident that the Quaker confeſſes him not come in fleſh all the Apoſtles did, ſo as through the breaking of it, and blood-ſheding of it, to effect mans ſalvation; but the body that doth this, we know not what it is (ſaith <hi>Lawſon</hi>) yea ſo ſlender a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect have they to his body of fleſh, that they deny the glorification of it, and ſo its aſcenſion into Heaven, and ſo now (ſay they) hath it not; and this they manifeſt, by ſaying Chriſt is already come the ſecond time, and looking for him to come no otherwiſe; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over theſe men makes void the ordinance of the Lords ſupper, which was inſtituted to hold forth (by a reſemblance) the breaking of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117938:22"/>body of Chriſt, and the ſhedding of his blood, which was ſhed for the remiſſion of ſins; this I ſay they totally diſ-own, as a carnal thing by which they ſhow their low eſteem of that which is ſignified by it, having conceived to themſelves a body, and blood in a myſtery, that ſets free from ſin; which we find not according to the Law, and Teſtimony, therefore it proceeds from darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>This is (ſaith the Quaker) a knowing Chriſt after the fleſh,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The diligent Scripture-ſearching ſoul may find, that the knowing of Chriſt, reconciling men in the body of his fleſh, through death, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.22. and his being now glorified therein, is not a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt after the fleſh; for equally as the Apoſtles knew not Chriſt after the fleſh; ſo they knew not the Saints after the fleſh, but them they could not know, as not having bodies of fleſh, neither as not to practice with their bodies, through the Spirit, for themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the ſame people to glorifie God both in their body and in their Spirit, (which ſaith the Apoſtle) are Gods, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. which bodies being ſown in the earth, they teſtified ſhould be raiſed again glorified, ſo that by this the Apoſtles did not in the leaſt ſlight the fleſhly body of Chriſt, nor the effects wrought for the ſons of men, by his being put to death in the fleſh; but having ſpoken at large before in the third chapter concerning the miniſtration of the Law, as done away, and of the preſent being of the more glorious mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Goſpel, concludes as to that, ſaying, that henceforth we know no man after the fleſh, yea though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, that is, had eſteem of him, in reference to the fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, birth-priviledged ſeed, of whom he came, as concerning the fleſh. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. thus the Apoſtles knew Chriſt no more, out rather as HE was declared to be the Son of God with power, according to the Spirit of holine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, by the reſurrection from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. and that <hi>Pauls</hi> intention, in ſlighting the knowing after the fleſh, is after this manner, is further evident <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3, 4. where he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelf, ſaith, that if any man might truſt in the fleſh, or have confidence in the fleſh, he might much more, and his reaſons are, becauſe he was circumciſed the eight day, of the ſtock of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin, &amp;c. verſ.</hi> 5. which plainly ſhews how men were known after the fleſh in the old miniſtration, which is now made void by the comming in of a more glorious miniſtration.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The fleſh profiteth nothing, ſaith Chriſt, from whence tis likely the Quaker will object.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:117938:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Conſider, we find the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> being one of them that Chriſt ſpake theſe words unto, teſtifying that Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſins, that he might bring us to God, being put to death in the fleſh, but quickened by the Spirit, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. now did not he, even HE underſtand Chriſt, though filled with his Spirit, which was to guide them into all truth, judge ye? and withall conſider the occaſion of theſe words of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.63. which was a propoſed queſtion by Chriſt himſelf, as appears <hi>verſe</hi> 62. what will ye ſay if ye ſhall ſee the ſon of man aſcend up where he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? the fleſh (ſaith Chriſt) profiteth nothing; (that is, in reference to his perſonall tarryance with his Diſciples) for tis (ſaith he) the Spirit that quickneth, which will not come unto you except I go away, wherefore Chriſt perſwadeth them that it was expedient for him to go away, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7. that is, to aſcend up where he was before; but as himſelf ſaith, he muſt FIRST ſuffer many things, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.25. yea and it behoved him thus to ſuffer, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.46. and what, doth this profit nothing? God forbid; for herein is the love of God manifeſted, in that, while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt dyed for us, who (at that time) ſaid to his Diſciples, that he gave HIS <hi>FLESH</hi> for the life of the World, <hi>verſe</hi> 51. that whoſoever eat thereof, and drink his blood (that is, as himſelf ſaith, beleeveth on mee) ſhall never hunger, nor thirſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 35. whoſoever therefore loves him not, let him be (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>Anathema, Maranatha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may ſerve alſo to diſcover the unlearnedneſſe of <hi>Lawſon,</hi> who cannot confeſs that Chriſt is a diſtinct being from the Father, though hee ſay, <hi>John</hi> 14.28. my Father is greater than I; unto whom he prayed, lifting up his eyes unto Heaven, <hi>John</hi> 17.1. who is now a MEDIATOR between God, and men, even the MAN Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. now if Chriſt be not diſtinctly conſidered, then how is he a mediator? for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith a mediator is not of one, but God is one, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.20. wherefore by this the Quaker is but the more revealed what he is; for conſider, the Spirit now dwelling in their fleſh, is alſo the Father, and Son, (in their account) and they look for him to come <hi>NO OTHERWISE,</hi> as ſaid <hi>George Fox,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many witneſſes; (the truth in Chriſt I ſpeak, and lye not) and ſo are they found to be the <hi>ANTICHRIST,</hi> that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, denying the Father, and the Son, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.22. in whoſe fear let us live, not <hi>TOUCHING THE UNCLEAN THING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaying, as aforeſaid, alſo ſaith, and indeed cannot but
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117938:23"/>ſay, that Chriſt aſcended not into Heaven, with that body which God raiſed from the dead, and glorified, and</hi> Thomas Laucock <hi>being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times asked by mee, where that Heaven was that Christ aſcended up into, and now was in, he anſwered, clapping his hands upon his breaſt, ſaying, WITHIN MEE, WITHIN MEE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Him, whom the <hi>Jews</hi> crucified on the tree, and ſlew, God rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the dead, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.39, 40. who being raiſed, bid his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples behold his hands, and feet, bidding them alſo to handle him, ſaying, a Spirit had not fleſh, and bones, as ye ſee mee have; HEE that was raiſed again, and THUS ſpake to his Diſciples, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39. HE led them out as far as to <hi>Bethany,</hi> and HE lift up his hands, and bleſſed him, <hi>verſe</hi> 50. and while HE bleſſed them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s parted from them, and carried UP INTO HEAVEN, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 51. and this is made good alſo by the Teſtimony of <hi>Stephen,</hi> who ſaid that hee ſaw the Heavens opened, and the SON OF MAN ſtanding on the right hand of God, even Jeſus whom God raiſed (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) from the dead, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. yea confirmed with his own Teſtimony, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.18. I am hee that liveth, and WAS DEAD, and behold, I live for evermore; wherefore I ſay; as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, LET ALL KNOW ASSUREDLY that God hath made the SAME JESUS, whom the <hi>Jews</hi> CRUCIFIED, both LORD and CHRIST, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36. but if any be ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and ignorant, as to beleeve that Heaven is within theſe mens mortall, and corruptible bodyes, and that Chriſt, whom the <hi>Jews</hi> crucified, is now dwelling therein, as his throne, and there is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God and men, let him bee, let him bee ignorant ſtill — that which is ſaid in the former particular, manages this truth alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaith, that ſome of them are already come unto the END OF FAITH, this</hi> Thomas Lawſon, John Slee <hi>gave mee in writing, which thing I denying, they thought it advantagious to their cauſe to publiſh it:</hi> Lawſ. <hi>book. pag.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>This their affirmation gives us to underſtand what glory (if I may ſay glory) it is they expect, and own, and moreover by this we may moſt clearly diſcern their denyall of the reſurrection, for otherwiſe they cannot ſay with any pretence, that they are NOW at the end of Faith; wherefore our confidence towards God, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117938:24"/>a reſurrection, is alone ſufficient to manifeſt the emptineſs of this ſaying of theirs; which they would eſtabliſh from <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to <hi>Timothy, ch.</hi> 1.9. Who hath ſaved us, &amp;c. but how? according to his own purpoſe, and grace given us (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>), in CHRIST JESUS, who is our life, and when he ſhall appear THEN ſhall we appear with him in glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. for unto them that LOOK for him, ſhall he appear the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. in which day, all tears ſhall be wiped awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but <hi>Timothy,</hi> who among others is ſaid there to be ſaved, was in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, even to tears, wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> had a great deſire to ſee him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mindfull of his TEARS, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. in that day alſo all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous, and miſery ſhall be done away, but <hi>Timothy</hi> is exhorted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of afflictions, and to endure hardneſſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 8.2, 3. more<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> the Scripture is able to make thee (not hath made thee) wiſe unto ſalvation, &amp;c. yea and that which is more plain, <hi>verſe</hi> 5. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> is ſaid to have unfeigned faith, and <hi>verſe</hi> 13. is exhorted to hold faſt the form of ſound words, in Faith, and Love; yet is this brought by <hi>Lawſon</hi> to prove that they were at the end of faith. Oh ſad blindneſs! how do they erre, not knowing, or rather ſlighting the Scriptures? — the ſumme of this is thus; the Quaker affirms, that Faith is at an end; <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, NOW ABIDETH FAITH, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. another Doctrin, another Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker alſo holds, that they are NOW in poſſeſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, and have eternall life really in POSSESSION.</hi> Lawſons <hi>book. pag.</hi> 9.19.</p>
            <p>Oh how are the right wayes of God perverted! what is it, that men come not to beleeve, when they leave the holy Scriptures as to be their rule? theſe men talk much of Light, but they that were in the Light indeed, teſtified that the Saints inheritance was RESER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VED in Heaven for them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. yet did they rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. through Faith in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which the holy men of old RECEIVED NOT, but died in Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13, 39 what hath not <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> received the Promiſes? and yet will theſe men ſay that they have? oh that they had a face, to bluſh at theſe things; how do they, in their conceptions, exalt themſelves above the Saints of old? yea above the Apoſtles; for hencerorth (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) there is LAID UP for mee a Crown of Righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. whoſe confidence was, that he ſhould be preſerved UNTO his heavenly Kingdome, <hi>verſe</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:117938:24"/>18. and ſo they witneſſed Chriſt to bee a Prieſt of good things, TO COME, <hi>Heb</hi> 9.11.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>This cannot be ſo ſaith</hi> Lawſon, <hi>becauſe Saints are ſaid to be delivered from the power of darkneſs, and tranſlated into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt,</hi> Col. 1.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Men before converſion are under the power of darkneſs, which is the broad way that leads to deſtruction; but being conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are on the contrary, under the power of Chriſt; and ſo are in the ready way to the poſſeſſion of the Kingdome; for unto that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry people that <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies thus to be tranſlated into the Kingdome; he ſpeaking of their hope, ſaid that it was LAID UP for them in Heaven <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. and to them alſo (he ſaith) ye know that of the Lord ye SHALL receive the reward of the inheritance, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.24. not HAVE received, therefore not in the poſſeſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; which is Saints reward; which they have now by promiſe, wherefore ſaith the Apoſtle, God hath choſen the poor of this world rich in faith, and HEIRS (not poſſeſſors) of the Kingdome, which he hath PROMISED to them that love him, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. this little will ſerve for them that owns the reſurrection, for the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of preſent poſſeſſion of eternall life (which is Saints reward) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the truth of that; wherefore let us give diligence to make our calling, and election SURE, and ſo an enterance ſhall be miniſtred unto us abundantly, into the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker alſo fully denieth the Reſurrection of the body, which they have often to me acknowledged, and</hi> Thomas Lawſon, John Slee <hi>(Quaker-teachers) gave me their underſtandings thereof in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (namely) that NOTHING that goes into the Grave ſhall riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt, I lye not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many are the ſhifts of them concerning this particular, inſomuch that ſometimes they do (by their DOUBLE-MEANING ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, perſwade enquiring Souls that they own the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſometimes alſo they endeavour to ſhew perſons their weakneſs, in ſearching after the Reſurrection, it being a deep myſtery; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, that they ought firſt to wait upon the light within, and that will reveal ſuch things unto them in due ſeaſon; and indeed hereby they ſhew that they have a ſpirit like <hi>Bala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ms;</hi> who being willing to anſwer the deſire of <hi>Balack</hi> (but could not, becauſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> was obedient according to the Scriptures) at length taught <hi>Balack</hi> to lay a ſtumbling-block before <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and when they forſook
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:117938:25"/>their God, in committing Whoredom, &amp;c. THEN <hi>Iſrael</hi> was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Curſe; ſo likewiſe doth the Quaker, endeavouring firſt to take off people from obſerving the Scriptures; as their rule, perſwading them to wait upon their light within, as the ONLY teacher; and when they have herein prevailed, then (oh then) the poor ſouls are ſubject to ſwallow in errors apace, yea though moſt plain, in oppoſition to the Scriptures, for otherwiſe they would not ſlight that cloud of Witneſſes, concerning the reſurrection from the dead; but though <hi>Iſrael</hi> play the harlot, yet let not <hi>Judah</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, but fear ye the Lord who is Almighty, and can as well raiſe up man again, after he is returned to duſt, as he did at firſt form him of the duſt of the earth; and withall ſearch yee the Scriptures; remembring that men formerly erred concerning the Reſurrection, not KNOWING THE SCRIPTURES, nor the POWER of God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.29. Conſider, Chriſt is ſaid to be the firſt fruits of them that ſleep, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20. the FIRST that ſhould riſe from the dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.23. and the Quakers myſtery may not here ſhow its ſelf, for Chriſt never was dead in ſin; but bodily dead he was, and the ſame body which was laid in the Sepulchre, God raiſed, as is evident, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.3, 5, 6, 12. who being raiſed, teſtified that he had fleſh, and bones, <hi>verſ.</hi> 39. but yet in a glorious manner; thus was Chriſt the firſt that roſe from the dead; now if the fleſhly bodies of men ſhall not alſo ariſe, and be made glorious, conſider how Chriſt can be ſaid to be the FIRST that roſe from the dead; for where there is not a ſecond, there cannot be a firſt; wherefore it follows, that the Sons of Men ſhall be raiſed in the likeneſs of his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; wherefore the Apoſtle makes the Reſurrection of Chriſt his firſt, and great Argument to ſatisfie the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that ſtaggered about the Reſurrection; concluding that men muſt needs riſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt was riſen; to which agrees the words of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28, 29. the hour is COMING, in the which all that are in the Graves ſhall hear his voyce, and ſhall come forth, they that have done good unto the Reſurrection of Life, and they which have done evil unto the Reſurrection of Damnation; but when I have produced this to theſe men, they ſlight the pure intention thereof, and tell me, that I am NOW in the grave there ſpoken of, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the grave of ſin; O remember the myſtery of iniquity, that is to be revealed in the laſt dayes! which hath here no place, though it ſhrouds its ſelf in with his fig-leaved garments, but truth diſcovers its nakedneſſe; for by graves, cannot be meant graves of ſin, in this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117938:25"/>place; firſt, becauſe Chriſt had ſpoken before in the 25. <hi>verſe</hi> of men dead in ſin (whom the Quaker ſuppoſes are in their graves) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the dead ſhall hear the voice of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall live; (ſecondly) becauſe of the time mentioned by Chriſt, when this riſing again from the grave ſhould be, which he ſignifies in theſe words; the hour is COMMING, not come, and now is, as he ſaid before, when he ſpake of riſing from deadneſs in ſin, which had been true, provided his meaning had been as the Quaker would have it; for men were as really riſen from ſin then, as now; (thirdly) becauſe ſome that riſe out of the graves, there ſpoken of, are ſignified to riſe fit for damnation, but thoſe that riſe from ſin, are fit for ſalvation; (fourthly) becauſe otherſome that riſe, or come forth out of the graves here ſpoken of, are ſuch as HAVE done good, and ſo are ſubjects of life, in reference to what they HAVE done before they riſe from the grave, which could not be ſo, if it be meant the graves of ſin, for the wages of ſin is death; to this agrees the anſwer of Chriſt, to the Sadduces queſtion (to wit) whoſe wife of the ſeven ſhe ſhould be in the reſurrection, when they ſhall riſe? for ſaith Chriſt, when they SHALL RISE from the dead, &amp;c. ſignifying that ſhould certainly riſe again, yea from that death, which cannot poſſibly be underſtood a death in ſin; the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the queſtion being conſidered; alſo in the reſurrection where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Chriſt ſpeaks, they ſhall neither marry, nor are given in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, but are as the Angels of God, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.23, 25. wherefore moſt plainly it appears, that by theſe words Chriſt preached up the reſurrection of the body, for from the beginning, perſons riſen from ſin did marry, and were given in marriage, and after Chriſt ſpake theſe words, it was accounted honourable by the Children of God, and is now ſo to be; to this agrees alſo the voice of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19. thy dead men ſhall live, together with my dead body ſhall they ariſe, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead; and ſaith <hi>Daniel,</hi> many that ſleep in the duſt of the earth, ſhall awake, yea from ſuch a death as ſome awakes from it, to ſhame, and everlaſting contempt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. and in this truth was <hi>Job</hi> well ſatisfied, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he wiſhed his words were printed in a book, and graven with an Iron Pen, in the rock for ever; ſaying, in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God, whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and not another, though my reins be conſumed within mee, and after my skin worms deſtroy this body, <hi>Job</hi> 19.23, 24, 25, 26, 27.</p>
            <p>Object. Job <hi>ſaw God in his fleſh</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Lawſon) <hi>with a ſpiritual
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117938:26"/>eye, before his returning to the dust,</hi> Job 42.5, 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Jobs</hi> testimony concerning his ſeeing God, then is not to be ſlighted, neither that of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> who alſo, and after the like manner, talked with God, and ſaw God; yet they dyed in Faith, NOT receiving the promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. the Prophet alſo bearing teſtimony, ſaying, though <hi>Abraham</hi> be IGNORANT of us, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> acknowledge us not, yet there is a time that ſhall come; and will come (ſpoken of by Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.28, 29.) when <hi>Abraham, Iſaack,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and al the Prophets, with many that ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, from the North, and from the South, and ſhall ſit down in the Kingdome of God; and to this agrees the words of <hi>Job,</hi> ſpeaking of his ſeeing God, but the time when, he intimates to be after his body was deſtroyed by worms, and the conſuming of his reins within him; which had not been when he ſpake theſe words, <hi>Job</hi> 42. read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over if it were true that theſe men were in the reſurrection, and ſo in the Kingdome (as they ſay they are) then ſhould thoſe that are thruſt out, in their account, SEE <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all the Prophets, in the Kingdome with them in glory, and themſelves, weeping, and gnaſhing their teeth; for ſo ſaid Chriſt to the rebellious <hi>Jews,</hi> Luk. 13.28. but this, with many more things, which ſhall appear in the reſurrection, now appears not, yet will they ſay that they NOW are in the reſurrection; oh STRONG DELUSION!</p>
            <p>The truth of this is yet further evident; for (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) ſince by man came death, by man came alſo the reſurrection from the dead, for as in <hi>Adam</hi> all dye, even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21.22. that is from that death, occaſioned by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, which God tells us was a returning to the duſt; of that which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the duſt, or ground, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. which we know was the fleſhly body of man, which by reaſon of ſin muſt dye, but through Chriſt all ſhall be made alive again; now wee know that all are not made alive from a ſpirituall death, therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaks not here of that, but indeed of the fleſhly bodies of men that are buried, or ſown into the earth, (even as the ſown Corn, which cannot hold compariſon with any thing elſe of man) which he teſtifies ſhall riſe again, ſaying, that THIS corruptible, muſt put on incorruption, THIS mortall muſt put on immortality, <hi>verſe</hi> 53. marke, not an immortal body, of other matter, but THIS which is now mortall, now corruptible, ſhall be made immortall, incorruptible, and ſo is made good the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. who ſhall change
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117938:26"/>our VILE body, that IT may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body; but the Quaker having another Spirit, ſaies that it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come out of the grave; but a laſſe, how greatly do they erre while they leave the Scriptures, as not to be their rule! wherein is clearly teſtified the conqueſt of the grave, for, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. O grave, I will be thy deſtruction; wherefore the Sea ſhall deliver up all that are in it; Hell, or grave, ſhall deliver up all that are in it, and death which feeds on many, that were never buried in the earth, or in the Sea, ſhall alſo bee delivered up, and ſo all ſhall come to judgement, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.13. this is certain, for repentance is hid from mine eyes, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. but according to the Quakers opinion, the grave is the conquerer (having got the bodyes of men in it, and ſo holds them faſt for ever, ſaith <hi>Lawſon</hi>) that is original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Devil; but Chriſt in the Apoſtles account; oh let him be alſo in our account, even him who through death hath deſtroyed him that hath the power of death, (that is the Devil) who will in his time, ranſome all from the power of the grave; O remember <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneus,</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> who are men branded with error, for ſaying the reſurrection was paſt already, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.18.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Quaker ſaith this cannot be ſo, becauſe</hi> (Paul <hi>ſaith</hi>) <hi>fleſh and blood connot inherit the Kingdom of God, — and thou ſoweſt not that body that ſhall be, but God giveth it a body, as it hath pleaſed him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True it is, that fleſh, and blood, as now it is corruptible, cannot inherit, wherefore the Apoſtle afterwards ſaith, that it muſt put on incorruption, then ſhall it inherit the incorruptible inheritance; and ſo is made good the compariſon (thou ſoweſt not that body that ſhall be) for we ſow, that is, commit mans body to the duſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, but God giveth it a body as it hath pleaſed him, even an incorruptible body; that is, raiſes the body which was ſown corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, in an incorruptible condition, ſo it is, that to every ſeed is given HIS OWN BODY; for the Corn conſumes not away, which is ſown into the earth, neither there abides, but the very ſame ſprings up again to its proper body, but more excellent through a change: and even ſo our vile body ſhall be changed and made like unto his glorious body, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. wherefore the ſumme of all is thus.</p>
            <p>The bodies of men that are committed to the earth, CORRUP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIBLE, DISHONOURABLE, WEAK, NATURALL; (WHICH SO CONSIDERED CANNOT INHERIT THE KINGDOME OF GOD) SHALL RISE AGAIN,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117938:27"/>INCORRUPTIBLE, HONOURABLE, POWERFULL, SPIRITUALL, AND SO CONSIDERED SHALL IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HERIT THE KINGDOME OF GOD, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43, 44. the Lord hath ſaid it, and who can diſannul it?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>It is the pure inſide of the Corn that ſprings up again, and not the ſhuck with it, ſo it is the internal Spirit of man that ſhall be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and not the body of fleſh, which is as the ſhucke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Moſt evident it is, that that, and ſo much of man, as is SOWN into the earth, is reſembled by the ſown corn; now the Spirit returns to God that gave it, and the fleſhly bodies are ſown into the earth, reſembled by the Corn that is ſown into the earth; and God gives it, marke, it is not ſaid that he gives, or makes A body, as if it were another in reſpect of matter, but gives IT, even IT that was ſown into the earth, a body glorious, immortall, as it hath pleaſed him; this is evident if the reaſoning with fleſh and blood be ommitted, and the holy Scriptures conſidered, which teſtifies of the GRAVES OPENING, and the DEAD bodies ariſing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.52. that is to ſay, SO FAR as they conſiſt of the PURE CREATION.</p>
            <p>Object. Paul <hi>tells the Saints that they were riſen with Chriſt,</hi> Col. 2.3. ch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He doth indeed repreſent them as riſen with Chriſt, but ſaith he through Faith, of the operation of God, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. which evidences things not ſeen, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. wherefore he tells them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that their life was HID with Chriſt in God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.3. and when Chriſt did appear, THEN they ſhould appear with him in glory; <hi>verſe</hi> 4. to which agrees theſe words, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.6, 7. God, who is rich in mercy, hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in heavenly places IN CHRIST JESUS, that in the ages TO COME, hee might ſhew the riches of his grace towards us; even at the reſurrection day, when Saints ſhall be rewarded, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.14. unto which they had not attained, for <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, the Teacher of them, ſtrongly affirms, that HE had NOT attained unto the reſurrection of the dead, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11, 12. but laboured that he might attain (that is) to the reſurrection unto life, at the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Jeſus, which he might come ſhort of, if not diligent; though notwithſtanding come to a reſurrection; but great was his deſire; O let it be even our deſires alſo, to be of that number that ſhal be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and meet the Lord in the air, and ſo EVER be with the Lord, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. at which time <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117938:27"/>reſt of the Saints that dyed in Chriſt ſhall riſe; though the Prophet have ſaid that <hi>Abraham</hi> was IGNORANT of them, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> acknowledged them not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16. and the Apoſtle bare record, ſaying, that they RECEIVED NOT the Promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. but Chriſt teſtifies of a time when they ſhall ſit down in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.28, 29. in reference to which time God ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he was the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> as appears by Chriſt, who teſtified that God is not a God of the dead, but of the living, and ſo from this concludes, that they muſt needs riſe again, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.31, 32. God having provided ſome better thing for us, that they without us, ſhould not be made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40. this is the reſurrection which the Apoſtles preached, which was eſteemed ſtrange, which made <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, why ſhould it bee thought a thing incredible to you, that God ſhould raiſe the dead? <hi>Acts</hi> 26.8. now that the riſing from ſin (wherein men are ſaid to be dead) to newneſs of life, was accounted an incredible thing, I leave honeſt judicious ſouls to judge; this is the Reſurrection, concerning which <hi>Paul</hi> had hope towards God, both of the juſt, and unjuſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which (ſaith the Quaker) is the old corrupt man, riſing in a man, which is the unjuſt; and Chriſt, the Light riſing in the ſame man, is the juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo one man is to witneſs both the Reſurrection of the juſt, and unjuſt in himſelf. This have I been plainly told (I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt, I lye not) by one of them; well, and truly ſaid the Apoſtle, the MYSTERY OF INIQVITY, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7, 8. what had <hi>Paul</hi> hope towards God, that the Old corrupt Man ſhould riſe again, either in himſelf, or in any others? Oh how great alſo is the darkneſs of this myſtery!</p>
            <p>Moreover, men that are turned from ſin to a new life, cannot ſay, and ſay truly, and underſtandingly, that they are riſen AGAIN, becauſe they were always fallen, and dead in ſin; now the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is not only a riſing, but a riſing AGAIN, according to the true, proper, and prime ſignification of both the Latine <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſurrectio, a riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</note> Greek * word; wherefore, O friends, look to your ſelves, and hold FAST, FAST, the form of ſound words, as yee have been taught; ABOVNDING in the work of the Lord, for as much as yee know your labour is not in vain in the Lord; for thus ſaith the Lord, O GRAVE, I will be thy DESTRVCTION, repentance ſhall be HID from mine eyes, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:117938:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker alſo ſaith, that the eternal Judgement is PAST already as to them, having (as they ſay) given an account to God already, for all that they have done, and RECEIVED THE REWARD FOR THEIR SINS, even WRATH, and CONDEMNATION; that is, the wounds of Conſcience, and the like; this, and more to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you may finde in</hi> Desburies <hi>Book, called,</hi> A Diſcovery of Mans return to his firſt eſtate, <hi>pag.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>This, will they ſay, proceeds from the light, but Chriſt, the LIGHT INDEED, diſcovers it to bee groſs darkneſs; who ſpeaking of rebellious <hi>Capernaum,</hi> ſaid, that it SHALL be more tollerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> in the DAY OF JUDGEMENT than for thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.24. now we know that <hi>Sodom</hi> was deſtroyed long before for their great wickedneſs, for which no doubt they had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wounds of Conſcience, yet repented not, and this was not in Chriſts account, the Judgement, for he ſpeaks of that as to come; and ſo is made good that ſaying, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. It is appointed unto men one to dye, but AFTER THIS the Judgement; alas, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, how doth vain thoughts lodge within theſe men? how greatly are they deceived! while they ſlight the true uſe of the Scriptures, which (before the ſtrong deluſion ſeiſed upon them) would have ſhewen them, that the Lord cometh with, not in, but WITH ten thouſand of his Saints, to excute judgement, <hi>Jud.</hi> 14.15. this <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> looked for (yet men of high degrees of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity) ſaying, We muſt all appear before the Judgement Seat of Chriſt; but (ſaith the Quaker) we HAVE appeared: another Doctrin (O Friends) wherefore another ſpirit; but unto us, that look for the Lord Jeſus from Heaven, who ſhall judge the quick and dead at his appearing, and his Kingdom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. unto us, I ſay, a little may ſuffice, for the manifeſtation of this errour,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker alſo beleeves, that ſin is NOT the cauſe of mans body returning to the duſt, as</hi> Tho. Lawſon, Tho. Laucock <hi>affirmed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Strange, yea very ſtrange is this ſaying, conſidered nakedly by it ſelf, but conſidering that it comes from a ſpirit that denies the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body, it is not ſo ſtrange; yet nevertheleſs the errour thereof is not thereby leſſened: Errour, I ſay, for when <hi>Adam</hi> by eating had ſinned, God ſaid unto him, BECAUSE thou
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117938:28"/>haſt eaten of the tree, of which I commanded thee ſaying, thou ſhalt not eat of it; curſed is the ground for thy ſake, in the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eate bread, till thou return unto the ground, for duſt thou art, and unto duſt ſhalt thou return; and to this agrees the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. As by one man ſin entred into the Word, and death BY SIN, and ſo Death paſſed upon all; not ſuch a Spiritual death as the Quaker would have, becauſe in Chriſt all ſhall be made alive from it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21, 22. hee having (through his appearance in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh) condemned ſin in the fleſh, which is the ſting of that death which brings into the Grave the bodies of men, <hi>verſ.</hi> 55, 56. thus by ſin comes the death of the body, and not only ſo, for thoſe many Curſes, as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our bread in ſorrow, in the ſweat of our faces, women, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth Children in ſorrow, even theſe attends the bodies of men and women by reaſon of ſin, even BECAUSE thou haſt eaten, ſaith God; ſhewing that God at firſt, in his threat upon the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of his Law, intended puniſhment upon the body; that which did eat, and in eating ſinned, dyed; and ſo DEATH BY SIN, ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker alſo ſlights, and denies Baptiſm in Water, calling it a low Carnal thing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">This is ſignified by Naylor in his Book called, A Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Seed of God, Pag. 33, 34.</note> 
               <hi>pleading that it may be now taken away by them (they ſeeing it to be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) without any Scripture warrant; they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (as they ſay) that Spirit within them which gave it forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo, they will ſay, proceeds from the Light, but not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; for Chriſt (the true Light) was not aſhamed thereof, but was obedient, even to Baptiſm in water. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.16. alſo ſaid, that whoſoever is aſhamed of him, and his words, of him hee alſo will be aſhamed when he cometh in the glory of his Father; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore look to yourſelves, that yee be not beguiled of your faith, in this ſo plain a Commandement; and for your ſtedfaſtneſs therein, I do here repreſent unto you Three conſiderations, as reminding you of the ground for Baptiſm in Water.</p>
            <p>Firſt, remember that <hi>John</hi> teſtifies that he was ſent (from the Lord) to Baptiſe with Water, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.33. and in preaching Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and Baptiſm, for the remiſſion of ſins, he is ſaid to be a preparer of the way of the LORD, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.2.3.4. in which Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117938:29"/>he was very famous, ſo that all the people went out unto him, to be baptized; but when Chriſt went forth, preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of the Kingdome, then the fame of <hi>John</hi> decreaſed; and all went out unto him, as moſt famous, <hi>John</hi> 3.26. at the hearing of which, <hi>John</hi> in all humility ſaid, hee muſt increaſe, but I muſt decreaſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Remember alſo that the Lord Jeſus, in plain words, gave it forth, by commandement, ſaying to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, &amp;c. that is, baptizing them in water, as unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyable appears, in that the DISCIPLES were to adminiſter it, (marke that) they could not, they did not baptize with the Spirit; but, ſaith <hi>John,</hi> (ſpeaking of Chriſt) he that commeth after mee, whoſe ſhoes I am not worthy to bear, HE ſhall baptize you with the holy Spirit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. which (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi>) GOD hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them that obey him, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.32. the glory of this miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Lord hath reſerved unto himſelf, and hath no where gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it to man.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Remember alſo that as baptiſme in water in <hi>Johns</hi> time, was with other things, a preparation of the way of the Lord, and afterwards eſtabliſhed by the ſpeciall command of the Lord himſelf, ſo alſo (after his aſcenſion) was it confirmed by an Angel from the Lord, who (well knowing his meſſage) bid <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſend for <hi>Peter,</hi> and he (ſaith the Angel) ſhall tell thee what thou ought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt (he ſaith not, what he might do, as an indifferent thing) but what thou OUGHTEST to do, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.5, 6. who, then he was come, and had ſeen the goodneſſe of God, ſaid, who can forbid WATER, that theſe ſhould not be baptized, which have received the holy Ghoſt, as well as we? making their receiving the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a great argument why they ſhould be baptized with water; yet will men uſe the ſame argument, why they need not be baptized with water; alaſs, alaſs, what will the poor ſoules anſwer, when God riſeth up? <hi>Job</hi> 31.14. theſe, even the Spirit-baptized people, <hi>Peter</hi> commands to be baptized, <hi>verſe</hi> 47, 48. wherefore, whatever men ſay, this being ſubmitted unto, from an inward principle of love, to him that firſt loved us, is not a carnal thing, but to be held faſt; remember, that Jeſus is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever.</p>
            <p>Object. Paul <hi>ſaid that Chriſt ſent him not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:117938:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt alſo ſaid, labour NOT for the meat that periſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but for that meat which endureth unto everlaſting life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27. what, did he hereby make void moderate working? ſurely nay; for <hi>Paul</hi> having his Spirit, ſaid, if any would not work, neither ſhould he eat; but rather that men ſhould not make it their SPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIALL labour, (as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, <hi>verſe</hi> 26.) after the things for the preſent, bodily ſubſiſtance; ſo <hi>Pauls</hi> ESPECIALL work was not to baptize (that is, perſonally to adminiſter baptiſme) but to preach the Goſpel, to which belongs baptiſme; unleſſe we ſhould beleeve that he preached one Doctrin, and <hi>Peter</hi> another, but that is incredible; but credible it is that they did not alwaies perſonally adminiſter it, and ſo it was that <hi>Paul</hi> had baptized but few of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> for which he gave God thanks, not from a low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem thereto, but becauſe they thereby had no ſhow, to ſay that he baptized in his own name; as they were apt to ſay, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, 14, 15. wherefore (O friends) as ye have received, hold faſt, and grow, as to the uſe of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker alſo denies the practice of the Lords ſupper, which</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Lawſon) <hi>Chriſt put to an end at his death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no marvel that they deny this, ſince they are not afraid to ſay, that the body, and blood of Chriſt, is unprofitable, (as to the ſetting free from ſin) which is to be in this remembred; but unto us, to whom the one is eſteemable, let the other alſo; for indeed it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to affirm that Chriſt ſhould give forth a commandement to his Apoſtles, bidding them to do it, in remembrance of him, and within four or five dayes, put it to an end by his death, yea before they were, or could be in any conſiderable poſture to obſerve it; and yet afterwards to command them to teach all Nations to obſerve all together incredible; moſt evident it is, that afterwards the Apoſtle delivered this ordinance unto the Saints, and afterwards regulated their diſorder therein, according to Chriſts inſtitution, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and the bread which they (in this ordinance uſed) <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith they BREAK, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. by which their myſtery is excluded, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (though <hi>Parnell</hi> be pleaſed to ſay, that this is a feeding upon husks) yet let us therein hold forth the Lords death, TILL HEE COME.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:117938:30"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Horrid Blasphemy of the Quaker revealed.</head>
               <p>MAny a time when I have ſpoken, both words of truth, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſs, the Quaker hath pronounced the curſes and plagues of God, to be my portion, which ſeemed not a little ſtrange unto mee; that men pretending perfection ſhould thus rage; but ſince I have found him, not afraid to ſpeak evil of the Lord himſelf, for more than once <hi>Thomas Laucock<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> (Quaker-teacher) hath ſaid that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is ACCURSED; him whom we profeſſe, even him that was born of the Virgin, anointed of God with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, whom the <hi>Jews</hi> crucified, and ſlew, whom God raiſed from the dead, who aſcended into Heaven, and there mediates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God, and men; this is the Chriſt whom we own, againſt whom the Quaker blaſpheming, is found not to have the Spirit of God, though he talk ſo much of the Spirit; for plainly, ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. NO man, ſpeaking by the Spirit of God, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Jeſus ACCURSED; and ſo being ſenſuall, having not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſaid at other times, that hee knew mee BEFORE THE WORLD WAS, in whom is made good that ſaying, (<hi>viz.</hi>) they ſpeak great SWELLING WORDS OF VANITY, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. and as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſieth, ſhall ſay in his heart, I will be LIKE THE MOST HIGH, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.14. for foreknowledge is that, by which God advanceth his ſupreamacy above all, wherefore it is ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.26. who hath declared from the beginning that wee may know? and before time, that wee may ſay hee is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous? yea there is none that declareth, there is none that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; yet ſaith <hi>Laucock;</hi> HE knew mee before the World was; and <hi>James Parnell</hi> ſaith, <note n="*" place="margin">In Naylers book called Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans deſign diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. p. 51.</note> before cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt reaſon was, I AM; Oh that they had ſuch a heart that could learn, not to blaſpheme! but this is that the Scripture might be fulfilled, which teſtifieth of this ſtrong deluſion; which being ſeized upon theſe men, they conceive the foreknowing God is ſo appeared in them, as that hee ſhall appear no otherwiſe, and ſo ſpeaks theſe words in them; what is there (O friends) that ever was ſpoken by the Lord himſelf, to the ſons of men, that theſe may not (upon this account) attribute unto themſelves, and ſpeak likewiſe? and what is there, of all that is to be done, by the mighty power of God, that theſe may not as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117938:30"/>well challenge unto themſelves (thus conceiving of God in them) as to ſay that THEY knew men before the World was? what is there to hinder them from ſaying, <hi>VENGEANCE BELONGS UNTO US?</hi> and ſo become the revealed <hi>SON OF PERDITION,</hi> who oppoſeth, and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, ſhewing himſelf that <hi>HE IS GOD,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3, 4. yea ſo ſtrong already are they in their conceits of the preſent finiſhing of things, as that <hi>Nayler</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Satans deſign diſcovered, p. 26.</note> blaſphemouſly affirms that to promiſe freedome after death is a <hi>CHEAT OF ANTICHRIST;</hi> and moreover ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">pa. 19.</note> that by preaching of a Chriſt in Heaven, the Devil gets his work done on earth. O how doth arrogancy, and ſpirituall pride put forth it ſelf! how great is the darkneſſe of this pretended Light! the imperfection, of this pretended perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction! ſuch alſo is their pride and ſelf-conceitedneſſe, as that they will not (by no means) ſay, <hi>MOST NOBLE FESTUS, Act.</hi> 26.25. but rather are ſuch as deſpiſe DOMINION, and ſpeak evill of dignities, <hi>Jude</hi> 8. but this alſo is, that the Scriptures might be fulfilled, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.20. whoſe look was MORE STOUT THAN HIS FELLOWS, fear yee the Lord, fear yee the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Scoffings of the Quaker manifeſted.</head>
               <p>AS we have heard that Scoffers ſhould come in the laſt dayes, even now already are they come, whereby we may know that it is the laſt of the laſt dayes; for at a certain time, when I, with other brethren, was reaſoning with <hi>Thomas Laucock;</hi> concerning the comming of Chriſt, he ſcoffingly ſaid, <hi>WHERE IS THE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISE OF HIS COMMING, IS HE ASLEEP?</hi> theſe very words (I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt, I lye not) did he utter, before many witneſſes; by which he is found to be of them, that <hi>Peter</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of, ſaying in the laſt dayes there ſhould come ſcoffers, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where is the promiſe of his comming? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3.4. he that by this ſees not, let him remain blind; moreover ſuch and ſo great is the darkneſſe of the Quaker concerning Chriſt, and his comming, as that at another time, in a conference about Chriſt in Heaven, he ſcoffingly replyed, ſaying, <hi>WHAT IS HEE, THREE, OR FOUR STORY HIGH, ABOVE SKIE?</hi> but ſaith the Saints, ſeeing then that we have a high Prieſt, that is paſſed into the Heavens, even
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117938:31"/>Jeſus the Son of God, let us hold faſt our profeſſion; but ſaith the ſcoffing Quaker, How can we have comfort or peace by Chriſt, and he ſo farre off from us, above skie? hee is (ſaith the Saints) gone into Heaven, whom having not ſeen yee love, in whom though now yee ſee him not, yet beleeving, yee rejoyce with joy UNSPEAKABLE, and FULL OF GLORY, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.8.3.22. whatever they ſay, he that SHALL come, WILL come, and will not tarry; fear yee the Lord, fear yee the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Fierceneſs, or Raylings of the Quaker diſcovered.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IVde</hi> the Servant of the Lord, ſpeaks of a people, that are as <hi>RA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GING</hi> waves of the Sea, foming out their own ſhame, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. how nigh of kin the Quaker is to them, judge yee by this following deſcription, of their behaviour towards me, when I have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, who at ſeveral times thus have ſaid to me in great rage, and fury of ſpirit; <hi>Thou Beaſt, bruit beaſt, thou Witch, thou Devil, thou Reprobate, thou Enemy of God, for the Lake, thou Swine feeding upon husks, thou</hi> Cain <hi>killing thy brother</hi> Abel, <hi>thou Drunkard, thou Thief, thou Murtherer, thou Serpent, the Curſes, Plagues, and Vengeance of God is thy portion,</hi> and ſaith <hi>Lawſon</hi> in his Book againſt me, <hi>Thou Image-maker, thou Cockatrice hatching Eggs, Vultures eye, (and this becauſe I ſaid,</hi> Chriſt was aſcended with that body that God raiſed from the dead) <hi>thou Heathen</hi> (becauſe I ſaid, the will of Chriſt was made known by the Scriptures) <hi>thou Lyar, bundle of Lyes, thou</hi> Eſau <hi>ſelling thy Birth-right,</hi> a <hi>Mate</hi> for the <hi>Night-birds, Cormorants, Bitterns, Owls, Ravens, Dragons, wild Beaſts, Satyrs, Vultures, Scritch-owles;</hi> (and this becauſe I ſaid that the Saints had not the Kingdom by poſſeſſion, but by promiſe; and when they thus with fury, and loftineſs of ſpirit, have pronounced Judgements, I have endeavoured to moderate theſe raging waves, but preſently it is replied, KNOW YEE NOT THAT THE SAINTS SHALL JVDGE THE WORLD? ſometimes alſo they endeavour to ſhelter themſelves with the expreſſions of Chriſt, and the Apoſtles; but conſider, did ever Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles, uſe ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to men, for preaching up the Kingdom (which is Saints reward) as by promiſe? nay himſelf did ſo; and his Apoſtles alſo; <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. or did they becauſe men ſearched the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, thereby to know the will of Chriſt? Nay ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117938:31"/>ſaith Chriſt; but indeed to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer, who had a long time before kicked againſt the counſel of the Lord, and would not CEASE to pervert the righteous wayes of God, to them they did SOMETIMES uſe ſome of thoſe expreſſions (which might be with a low Spirit delivered) but what is this to juſtifie the Quakers raging againſt men that hold forth the counſel of God? yea, and that at the firſt diſlike of their wayes; yea, and at all times, when oppoſed; nay, rather is hee found to bee of that number, that the Apoſtle propheſied of, ſaying, In the laſt dayes perillous times ſhall come, for men ſhall be FIERCE, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. their look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more <hi>STOUT THAN HIS FELLOWS, Dan.</hi> 7.20. but render YE not evill for evill, railing for railing, but contrariwiſe be ye tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, of a good behaviour, and <hi>HOLY IN ALL YOVR WAYES.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Abominable Deceit of the Quaker diſcovered.</head>
               <p>HOw far off the Miniſtry of the Quakers are from the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Miniſtry, who renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, not walking in craftineſſe, nor handling the Word of God deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. judge ye by theſe following lines, though I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but that many have experience of their deceit, as well as I; if you ask them, whether they own the reſurrection from the dead? they will (I ſay will, except they be changed) readily anſwer you, that they do; (but means, a preſent riſing from a dead condition in ſin;) whether they own a reſurrection from the grave? yea, (will they ſay) we do; (but mean, a riſing from the grave of ſin, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in living men now are) whether they own a reſurrection to come? yea, (will they ſay) we do; (but mean, a riſing from ſin to come, to <hi>OTHERS</hi>) but when I have asked them whether they own a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to come unto THEM? then <hi>SILENT FLESH, SI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENT;</hi> moreover, as I ſaid before, ſo I ſay again, that <hi>Thomas Lawſon</hi> plainly ſaid, that all that goes into the grave, ſhall never riſe again, which was written by his conſent, at my houſe; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in his book tells people, that he owns the reſurrection both of the juſt and unjuſt; and calls mee ſlanderer, for ſaying that hee denyed the Reſurrection; Now hee knows that wee and the major part of men, own the reſurrection of the bodyes of juſt and unjuſt men, which are commtited to the graves of the earth; but their meaning is, the riſing and being of the old corrupt nature in man (which they call the reſurrection of the unjuſt) and the riſing of Chriſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117938:32"/>the Light in man, as (they ſay) is the reſurrection of the juſt, which the Scripture ſpeaks of; and ſo they, NOW witneſſe both; this have I been plainly told by one of them, I ſpeak the Truth in Chriſt; O ſhamefull deceit! If you ask them, whether they own the coming of Chriſt? they will anſwer you, that they do; (but they mean, his coming to others) but when I have asked them, whether they own Chriſt to come to <hi>THEM?</hi> then <hi>SILENT FLESH, SILENT;</hi> but through importunity <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaid, that HE looked for him to come, no otherwiſe; the like will they ſay, concerning the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal judgement; likewiſe when we ſpeak of the Righteouſneſſe of God wrought through the perſon of Jeſus, as it was offered up; they will ſay, as <hi>Nayler</hi> hath ſaid, <note n="*" place="margin">Satans deſign diſeovered. pag. 4.</note> that they own no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther righteouſneſſe, than that which was wrought IN the perſon of Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> his ſuffering, reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and aſcenſion; (but they mean, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wrought BY the Spirit, IN that perſon; and the ſufferings of that Spirit IN that perſon, whoſe reſurrection is now within THEM, <note n="*" place="margin">Naylers book called a ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the feed of God. pa. 21.</note> excluding all this while the effect wrought BY the Perſon of Chriſt, offered up to death.) If you ask them, whether they own juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by the blood of Chriſt? they will anſwer, yea; (but they mean, blood myſteriouſly.) Whether hee died yea, or nay? they will ſay, yea alſo to that; (but they mean, death in a myſtery) for he that ſuffered, (ſaith <hi>Nayler</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Satans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, &amp;c. pa. 25.</note>) is NOW in his people, leading them through ſufferings, himſelf now ſuffering with them. If you ask them, whether they beleeve that Chriſt hath now a body? they will ſay, yea; (but they mean, his Church) Whether he aſcended into Heaven, yea, or nay? they will ſay, yea; (but ſaith <hi>Laucock,</hi> Chriſt is aſcended into Heaven WITHIN MEE) At a certain time having reaſoned with <hi>Lawſon</hi> concerning Gods making of the earth on which we went, and the Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, I asked him, whether Gods preſence was not more in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than on earth? to which he ſaid, yea, but being ſuſpicious of his deceit, asked him, whether he did not mean that he was more in heavenly-minded men, than in earthly-minded men? O then, how did he ſhuffle? conſider ye that fear God, whether this be not deceit, for men to anſwer plain-meaning queſtions, with ſuch double-meaning expreſſions, as may ſeem to agree with the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him that asks, and YET by the ſame words intend the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117938:32"/>contrary; what? is this the language of <hi>Canaan</hi> which they ſpeak of? nay, ſurely deceit is of the deceiver; TOUCH not the unclean thing; for bleſſed are the <hi>PVRE</hi> in heart, they ſhall ſee God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Diſhoneſty of the Quaker, in contending for his Principles, diſcovered.</head>
               <p>IF diſhoneſty in and about the things of this life, be odious in the ſight of God, and godly men; what may bee ſaid of men that ſhall defend, yea, unſound principles with impure diſhoneſt indeavours? and not only ſo, but in the mean time advance themſelves (by their ſuppoſed, pleaded-for perfection) above the Saints of old, that ſaid in many things we offend all: now that they ſo do, conſider theſe following paſſages; At a certain time I was in <hi>Lawſons</hi> ſociety, conferring about Chriſts words, <hi>viz.</hi> that no man could come to the Father but by him; to which I ſaid, that he was indeed the way to the Father, that is (ſaid I) through faith in his ſufferings, for by his perſon no man comes to the Father, conſidered without his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; from which words, and many more of this nature, he picks out theſe words, (that I ſaid) that no man comes to the Father by the perſon of Chriſt, and prints it in his book, though no more ground ſo to do, than he may have to ſay that <hi>David</hi> ſaid there was no God, leaving out the former words, <hi>viz.</hi> the fool hath ſaid in his heart; but that which aggravates his diſhoneſty is, that (while hee blames mee for diſowning the coming unto the Father by the perſon of Chriſt, when as I do not) himſelf doth, as hath been proved; and in his book elſewhere calls mee image-maker, for owning the perſon of Chriſt aſcended, and yet he, even HE upbraids mee for denying the coming unto the Father by the perſon of Chriſt; doth this (O friends) look like unto perfection? nay, rather an inexcuſable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, in that he blames another, and yet doth the thing, which hee blames another for, HIMSELF; at another time being greatly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided, for acknowledging my ſelf ſailable in ſome things, (by <hi>George Fox</hi>) I at length deſired him to conſider that which is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>Peter,</hi> who, (ſaid I) was eminent in the ſervice of Chriſt, yet ſinned; for the proof of which I read that in <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> where it is ſaid, that <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him to the face, becauſe he was to be blamed; and that he with other <hi>Jews</hi> diſſembled; which to any honeſt man is proof ſufficient; but ſo far was <hi>Fox</hi> from recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, that he furiouſly falls on calling mee beaſt, and lyer, becauſe I affirmed that <hi>Peter</hi> ſinned, and that word (SINNED) was not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117938:33"/>there; yet will this man ſay hee is perfect; but judge ye whether a man that is but a babe in Chriſtianity; would not abhorre ſuch a thing; for can it be thought that he that diſſembles, and is to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, is unblamable? moreover at another time I made repetition of this paſſage, before <hi>Thomas Laucock</hi> to hear what he would ſay to it, but in the leaſt would he not blame his Brother, but violently puts mee to prove that DISSIMULATION WAS SIN, <note n="*" place="margin">Many witneſſes hearing.</note> which at firſt I was unwilling to do, but being preſt to it by <hi>Laucock,</hi> I did produce Scriptures for the proof thereof; then ſaid one of them to mee, but was it ſin in <hi>Peter?</hi> are not theſe (O friends) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe reaſonings of men of corrupt minds? was it ever known ſince the World was, that a man ſhould be put to prove diſſimulation to be ſin? would any of the prophane World, the drunkard, or ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, thus reaſon? ſurely nay; but that which is moſtly to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is, that all this while they ſhould juſtifie themſelves, ſaying to all, STAND OFF, WE ARE PERFECT. Oh that the poor ſouls had hearts to conſider their great imperfection! at another time I being accuſed by <hi>Laucock,</hi> for putting the title (Brother) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one that was withdrawn from, endeavoured to prove the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof by the Scriptures, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14, 15. moreover I ſaid, it was clear according to a ſimilitude for (ſaid I) PROVIDED my finger, (pointing thereat) WERE cut, yet it is not preſently to be ſlighted, and cut off, but firſt to apply means of cure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> even ſo in the other; to which <hi>Laucock</hi> anſwered, ſaying, that I was a lyar, a lyar; if my finger was not really, and indeed cut; I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt, thus did he ſay, before ſeveral men; wherein he hath fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out his own ſhame; but this is that the Scriptures might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, which teſtifie, that in the laſt dayes, perillous times ſhall come, wherein men ſhall be — UNHOLY — FALSE ACCUSERS, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3. Oh let us be holy in all our wayes. This little, of much more of this nature, I offer unto your conſiderations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid, the Quaker looks upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as perfect, yea,</hi> (<hi>as</hi> Laucock <hi>hath ſaid</hi>) <hi>as PERFECT WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVT SIN, AS GOD IS; condemning others, becauſe they ſay with the Apoſtle, in many things we offend all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that is ſo ignorant as to beleeve this, let him be ignorant ſtill. Yet true it is, that Saints were perfect, and now may be perfect,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117938:33"/>(that is) as conſidered in Chriſt, who, of God, is made unto us wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption, unto whom we are now to live, and no longer unto our ſelves; even perfecting holineſſe in the fear of God; wherefore let every ſoul awake unto Righteouſneſs, and know for certainty, that perfection is farre more than the forſaking of the falſe worſhips of men, and the groſs crimes wherein we have lived, for that may be, and yet we ſhut out of the Kingdome, like fooliſh Virgins, that have not been zealous for God; far more alſo is it, than a walking blameleſſely to the view of men; for that a man may do, &amp; yet be defiled within, wherefore with the Apoſtle renounce the hidden things of diſhoneſty; even private, evill motions, which ſurely cannot but make the ſoul mourn, that truly fears God; for it is not a work done, but a work well done that is acceptable in the ſight of God; even when SELF is ſhut out, and not mixt with good intentions; yea and when the heart is affected with duty, which cannot bee till the ſoul is fixed upon the Lord, as the object of his affections, then, and not TILL THEN is there paſſage to perfection; for where the treaſure is, the heart WILL BEE; wherefore LOVE YEE THE LORD GOD WITH ALL YOUR SOULES, AND WITH ALL YOUR STRENGTH; yea and the Children of God alſo, with a pure heart fervently; yea, yet further muſt we go, if wee will bee perfect, even to the doing him good, that doth us evill; yea, and that with freedome of Spirit alſo.</p>
               <p>O then live in the fear of the Lord, crying mightily unto him, that from him you may receive ſuch meaſures of Grace, as that you may experience good degrees of Chriſtianity; and by no means ſhelter negligence, and coldneſſe, under the Apoſtles words (it is not I, but ſin that dwelleth in mee) but bee zealous, (as wiſe Virgins) ſo ſhall yee enter into the Kingdome; but if contrariwiſe you ſhall trifle away this day of liberty, which was purchaſed with much blood, what will yee anſwer, when God viſiteth? what will yee do when hee riſeth up, <hi>Job</hi> 31.13? wherefore redeem time, and apply your hearts unto wiſdome, and let every one attend upon his work; hear yee diligently, and do yee accordingly; yee that teach, teach in ſincerity, through the ability which God giveth, and let the ARTIFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIALL, METHODICALL, OLD-MAN-PLEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SING FORMS, in the miniſtration of the word, DIE
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117938:34"/>DAYLY, wait yee upon the Lord; Again I ſay, wait upon the Lord; yea, and let us all ſerve the Lord in ſimplicity of heart; O LET OUR SOULES, OUR SOULES follow HARD after the Lord, WATCHING, AND PRAYING, PRAYING WITH FASTING.</p>
               <p>Hee that ſhall come WILL come, and will not tarry: For hee is not ſlack concerning his promiſe (as ſome men count ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) but is long ſuffering, not willing that any ſhould periſh. NOW the juſt ſhall live by faith.</p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:117938:34"/>
            <head>Antichriſt made known; OR, The Romiſh VVhore of Babylon proved not to bee the Antichriſt, or Man of Sin, In ſeven particulars.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Who is this great Whore of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and where her chief Seat hath been, and is?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Her Fall, and the means how and by whom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>What is the spirit of Antichriſt, and who hath that ſpirit?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>That the Antichriſt will bee a ſingle perſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>The manner of his riſing, And when.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 <hi>Some of the great things hee will do.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. Laſtly, <hi>His Fall, when, and by whom.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Jeffery <hi>Servant of the Church of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any honeſt men fearing God in theſe latter times, have been miſtaken in ſaying that the Romiſh Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> is the Antichriſt that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks of; but men may ſee in this latter part of this laſt time, with a ſerious and diligent ſearch of the Scriptures, through grace, that the great Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> is not the Antichriſt; And it being ſo that God having ſhewed it mee through the Scriptures, I being not accounted of in the World, knowing that God doth great things by them that are not eſteemed among men, that no fleſh may glory, &amp;c and conſidering that this which I do in this work may bee ſeaſonable and for much profit to the people of God, and for the praiſe and glory of God, I ſhall ſhew in brief, <hi>that the Whore is not the Antichriſt. And for the clearing up of this Truth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, You may ſee who this great Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> is, by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her chief Seat where it is, and that is at <hi>Rome,</hi> for <hi>John</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:117938:35"/>
               <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. that the great Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which ſitteth upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters, is that City which reigneth over the Kings of the earth. Now <hi>Rome</hi> only was the chief City, and reigned over the Kings of the earth, when <hi>John</hi> wrote the <hi>Revelation,</hi> for when Chriſt was born <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> taxed all the World, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. and when <hi>Paul</hi> appeals to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> they ſend him to <hi>Rome,</hi> Acts 25.11. chap. 27.1. chap. 28.16. ſo it is plain by theſe Scriptures, and many more, that when <hi>John</hi> wrote the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that <hi>Rome</hi> reigned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Kings of the earth, therefore the chief Seat of this VVoman the great Whore, the Mother of Whoredoms, is the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo then the Pope and his Cardinals, Biſhops, and Clergy, and all Miniſters that have ordination from them immediately, or by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, which ſtand in a National way, is the Whore that ſits upon many waters; which is, people, and multitudes, and Nations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Tongues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all National ſtanding is truly ſaid to be whoriſh, becauſe ſhe bringeth in Members, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth them of the Body or Church of Chriſt by generation, and ſo maketh her Church National; whereas the Church of Chriſt is by Regeneration, or New Birth, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. and ſo not National, nor dependent, but particular, or independent.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This appeareth fully, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Harlots, and all National Churches that ſpring from her are Whoriſh, becauſe ſhe baptiſeth or ſprinkleth upon a fleſhly account, and ſo accounts of her Members in a fleſhly way by Generation, and ſo brings in Infants in a lineal way, bringing in the Old Covenant in a confuſed manner, and ſo receiveth falſe Seed, and ſo knoweth her Members, and her Children in a fleſhly way, contrary to the expreſs way of Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. ſaith he, They which are the children of the fleſh are not the Children of God, but the Children of the Promiſe are counted for the Seed; and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15, 16, 17. he ſheweth that ſince the death of Chriſt, henceforth know we no man after the fleſh, yea though we had known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet now henceforth know we him no more; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any man be in Chriſt he is a new Creature, old things are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away; behold all things are become new.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Lord Biſhops, and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which ſpring from her (for they hold their Ordination which they had of her) ſhew themſelves to be whoriſh, becauſe they have forſaken the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (the Head) and his ways, and have
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117938:35"/>gone a whoring after their own inventions, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 39. for the Lord Jeſus aſcended up on high, and gave gifts to men, and ſo ſends forth a Miniſtry by gifts, for the gathering together of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, and for edification of the Body of Chriſt, till we all meet together in the unity of the faith, and the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. but this Harlot contrariwiſe brings up her Miniſtry to Human learning, in ſending them to the Univerſities to learn Philoſophy from <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> a Heathen Author, and ſuch like; and for them that are gifted by the Lord, if they preach, ſhe forbids them. And note alſo, that the Miniſters of Chriſt miniſtring by gift, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7. being qualified according to this, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. and approved by the Congregation of the Lord, they are choſen by them, and ordained, and ſo made Biſhops, or Elders, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.21 to the end, chap. 6.5. chap. 14.23. but this Harlot makes her Miniſters, or rather Lords, without the conſent of her Pariſhes, and forceth them in upon them whether they will or no, and ſo her maintenance is by Tithes forced from men, bringing in the old Prieſthood; yea in the time of the Law they did not impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon men, if they did not pay their tithes that we find, and yet ſhee doth; and ſo this <hi>Romiſh</hi> Harlot which hath made all Nations drunk with the wine of her Fornication, her children are children of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, according to the fleſh by generation, a Carnal ſeed conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pariſhes, which many of them conſiſt of Swearers and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and Drunkards, and Whoremongers, and ſuch like, and a Human carnal Miniſtry forced upon the people, and forced main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and alſo her poor is maintained by force, and forcing men to worſhip with her, or elſe Fines, Impriſonment, Baniſhment, or Death muſt be their Portion, and alſo ſhe hath changed the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and the manner of adminiſtring them, and the ſubject, and ſo her way is not the way of love, and ſo not the way of Chriſt; and yet ſhe ſaith in her heart and word, I am, and there is none elſe, I ſit being a Queen, and am no Widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow; and ſo let every one (weigh well) what is ſaid, that the Saints at <hi>Rome</hi> were once famous, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. but in time they departed from their eſpouſed Chriſt the Lord, and ſo came to change the Ordinances, and yet ſhe pretends to be the Spouſe of Chriſt, and ſo hath a ſhew of all the Ordinances, or the names of them, for Beleevers Baptiſm ſhe hath Infants baptiſm, or ſprinkling, and for laying on of hands ſhe hath Confirmation, or Biſhopping (but the Presbyters have
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:117938:36"/>left this out, and in this they are neerer Antichriſt than the Lord Biſhops, and for breaking of Bread, or the Lords Suppor, that is in Part miniſtred to the People, or Pariſh, and ſo to the wrong ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, being not penitent, nor Baptiſed perſons; and inſtead of the true Call of her Miniſtry, ſhe hath a Human way, as hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is not mentioned in Scripture, and ſo Tithes and forced maintenance inſtead of that which is to be by free gift; and inſtead of ſinging with the ſpirit, and with the underſtanding alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15. they have ſinging in Rime, in a Carnal formal way, many to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without underſtanding, the Pſalms being collected into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Meeter by <hi>Thomas Sternhold, John Hopkins,</hi> and others, and ſo ſhe hath a glorious Show, and a golden Cup, and through the Popes Supremacy, and the Peter-pence, and Prayer to Saints, and falſe Doctrin of Purgatory, and ſuch like trumpery, the Clergy is very rich, and proud, and covetous, and ſo all may ſee the way of the Whore which is National, Generational, Fleſhly, Carnal, Human, after mens Traditions, making voyd the Commandements of God through her Traditions, thus ſhe goeth a whoring after her own inventions; and ſo you have a brief diſcovery of the Whore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> which is the Mother of abominations of the earth, and is drunken with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Jeſus. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17 5, 6. and that is and will be the cauſe of her Fall, and that brings mee to the ſecond thing, even the Fall of this Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the manner how and by whom. And for the clearing up of this,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider that this woman ſits upon a ſcarlet-coloured beaſt, full of the names of Blaſphemy, which had ſeven heads and ten horns <hi>Reve.</hi> 17.3. now note, that five of them heads, or Kings were faln when <hi>John</hi> wrote the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and the ſixt was then in being, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9, 10. now this woman the Harlot was to ſit upon the ſixt head, and hath ſo done a long time, and ſo the beaſt that had ſeven heads carrieth her, and beareth her up, for the Magiſtrates have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported her all along, underſtand alſo, that the ſixth head of the beaſt hath reigned ever ſince the writing of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> but now is partly ſtrong, and partly broken, and that the ſixt head is not fallen, is plain if you note well, for the ſeventh head when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he muſt continue a ſhort ſpace, now that head of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy which is in being, hath coutinued long, even from before the birth of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this the Scripture clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10. five are fallen, and one is, and another is not <hi>yet come, and when hee
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:117938:36"/>comet<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hee muſt continue a ſhort ſpace; the power of the Pope and his Clergy cannot be the ſeventh head, for that hath continued long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Whore cannot bee any of the heads of the beaſt, becauſe ſhe ſits upon, <hi>and is carried by the beaſt that hath ſeven heads, and ten horns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So ſhe cauſeth the beaſt to ſerve her, and maketh the beaſts and the Kings of the earth ſlaves to her, to do her will; ſo then the ſixth head of the <hi>Roman</hi> power is not fallen, though it be in part; and the ſeventh head is now ariſing, which will take away the ſixth, and doth, will, and muſt give ſome liberty to preach the Goſpel, and to adminiſter the Ordinances in the old way thereof, and ſo the Lord God will bring things to paſſe, for not one jot or tittle of his word ſhall fall, and ſo in the riſing and reign of the ſeventh head, and of the ten horns, the Angel ſhall flye in the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting Goſpel, to preach unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every Nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people, ſaying with a loud voice, fear God, and give glory to him, for the hour of his Judgement is come, and worſhip him that made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and the fountains of waters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6, 7. ſo the Goſpel and the way thereof being preached, the Nations will bee enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſo God will put it into the hearts of the ten horns, or Kings, to hate the Whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12, 16. ſo through the preaching of the Goſpel in the pure way thereof, the great Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> falleth, and ſo the hour of her Judgement is come; and to this agreeth that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6, 7, 8. which ſheweth, that after the Goſpel is preached to the Nations, then ſhall follow another Angel ſaying, it is fallen, it is fallen, <hi>Babylon</hi> the great City, for ſhe made all Nations to drink of the Wine of the wrath of her fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. much more might bee ſpoken to this, but let this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as touching what the Whore is, and her fall, the manner how, and by whom.</p>
            <p>In the next place, note diligently what the ſpirit of Antichriſt is, and who have that ſpirit; now <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, <hi>chap.</hi> 4. and <hi>verſe</hi> 3. doth declare what the ſpirit of Antichriſt is, namely, every ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God, and this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt, whereof you have heard that he ſhould come, and even now already is in the World. Alſo underſtand, that <hi>John</hi> did not intend ſimply the Heathen that never did beleeve, nor the unbeleeving <hi>Jews,</hi> which never did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:117938:37"/>Chriſt come in the fleſh, but thoſe have the ſpirit of Antichriſt that went out from (the Churth of Chriſt) <hi>chap.</hi> 2.18, 19. <hi>John</hi> ſheweth them that it is the laſt time, and as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee know that it is the laſt time, THEY WENT OUT FROM US, &amp;c. ſo that the ſpirit of Antichriſt is that ſpirit that is found in them that have been enlightened, and have known the truth, and go out from the Church of Chriſt, and in a myſtery deny Chriſt come in the fleſh; and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Antichriſt, or man of ſin, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. ſaith, the MYSTERY of iniquity doth already work, &amp;c. and <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking to the Saints, ſaith (in his ſecond Epiſtle, 2.1.) there ſhall be falſe teachers among you, who PRIVILY ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying THE LORD THAT BOUGHT THEM, and bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſwift deſtruction. So the ſpirit of Antichriſt denies Chriſt come in the fleſh ſecretly, and they that have this ſpirit, ſay, Chriſt is come in their fleſh, and ſo ſay the light within them is Chriſt, <hi>when at the beſt it is but the light of nature,</hi> and in many the ſpirit of errour, their light being become darkneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being delivered up to ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, to beleeve lyes, thinking they have Chriſt in them, when it is a ſpirit of errour, and ſo pervert the ſenſe of the Scriptures, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the anointing, and the anointed to be all one, teaching up the Spirit of Chriſt, apart from the body of Chriſt, to be the Chriſt, or rather the ſpirit of errour in them, to be the Chriſt come in their fleſh, and ſo in a very deceivable ſecret way, deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, in ſaying he is the Chriſt that is within them, which is an evill ſpirit, ſo applying the Scriptures that ſpeak of the Spirit of Chriſt dwelling in men, to be that evill ſpirit in them, ſo declaring that Spirit of errour in them apart from the body or fleſh of Chriſt, to bee the Chriſt, and ſo deny Chriſt come in the fleſh; but note well, what the Scripture; of truth ſaith, they declare that Jeſus the Chriſt was ſlain, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.22 23. chap. 3. 5. chap. 4.10. in chap. 5 30. <hi>Peter</hi> who was ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Holy Ghoſt, ſaith, the God of our Fathers hath raiſed up Jeſus, whom ye SLEW and HANGED on a tree; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3, 4. firſt of all, I delivered unto you, that which I received how that CHRIST DY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED FOR OVR SINS, according to the Scriptures, and that he was BVRIED, and that he AROSE the third day according to the Scriptures; ſo it is plain, that the Spirit apart from the body or fleſh of Chriſt, is not the Chriſt. And therefore again note, what
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:117938:37"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. There is one God, and one Mediatour, BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TWEEN God and man, which is the MAN Chriſt Jeſus; and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10 ſheweth that the Hebrews were ſanctified by the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the BODY of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 19, 20. ſeeing therefore Brethren, that by the BLOOD of Jeſus, we may be bold to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the holy places by the new and living way which he hath conſecrated for us, through the veil, that is, his FLESH. So that Jeſus, that was baptized of <hi>John</hi> in the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> was anointed with the oyl of gladneſſe above his fellows, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.13, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7. ſo Jeſus the Saviour is the anointed of God, for he gave him not the Spirit by meaſure, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.34. and ſo the Spirit of the Lord reſteth and abideth upon the MAN Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.32. ſo then the Spirit of God, or of Chriſt, apart from the BO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DY of Chriſt, is not the Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore moſt abominable is that which men ſay, that that which is in them is Chriſt, when it is a ſpirit of errour, <hi>and ſo men may ſee how through this myſtery of iniquity, men come to ſay they are Chriſt; for conſider, if the ſpirit in ſome man be the Chriſt, what hindreth him to ſay hee is Chriſt,</hi> and therefore ſome one preſumes to ſay hee is Chriſt; let no man miſtake mee, for I ſay that the Spirit of God doth dwell in the Saints, and that Chriſt doth dwell in their hearts by faith; but note, that faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. ſo the juſt live by faith, and look for the Son of God from Heaven, whom he raiſed from the dead, even Jeſus that delivereth us from the wrath to come; but to return, ſo as to ſhew yet further who hath the ſpirit of Antichriſt, and they are ſuch as race out the Ordinances of Chriſt, which came in being, when Chriſt came in the fleſh, and ſo declare Chriſt come in the fleſh, dead, and riſen again, as baptiſm of water, and breaking of bread, which doth declare the Lords death till he comes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Rom</hi> 6.3, 4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. now there are a ſort of men which ſay, to know or acknowledge Chriſt in the practice of thoſe Ordinances, is formall, and fleſhly, and low, and carnal, and ſo reject the Counſel of God, and will not be baptized; and ſo not walking up in the Ordinances that did come in being, when Chriſt came in the fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and do ſo excellently declare him come in the fleſh, and are to continue unti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Chriſt come from Heaven, and change our vile bodies, and make them like his moſt glorious body, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20, 21. I ſay thoſe that do ſlight and reject thoſe ordinances, and ſay they are formall, and will not practice them, have the ſpirit of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:117938:38"/>Antichriſt, and do deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, becauſe they will not practice thoſe ordinances that declare Chriſt come in the fleſh, yea, more fully than the Whore, for ſhee hath a ſhew, and ſo a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe Ordinances, though ſhe have changed the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the manner, as aforeſaid; but THESE root out the very being of them, and ſo deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, and ſo are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to have the ſpirit of Antichriſt, alſo thoſe that have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, and have beleeved the Reſurrection of the body, and alſo the eternal Judgement, and then come to queſtion it, and deny it, and ſay, the Judgement day is come, have the ſpirit of Antichriſt, for Chriſt being put to death in the fleſh, and riſing again from the dead, ſo bringeth in the Reſurrection of the bodyes of all men, and then cometh in the eternal Judgement, according to that in <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30, 31. hee hath appointed a day in the which he will judge the World in Righteouſneſſe, by that MAN whom he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whereof he hath given aſſurance to all men, in that he hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him from the dead, ſo as by man came death, by man came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the reſurrection of the dead, for as in <hi>Adam</hi> all dye, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all bee made alive, but every man in his own order, the firſt fruits is Chriſt, afterwards they that are of Chriſt, at his comming, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21, 22, 23. ſo Chriſt being come in the fleſh, the MAN Chriſt Saviour, dyed and roſe again, and ſo comes in the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and no otherwiſe; therefore they that deny the Reſurrection of the body, deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, and ſo have the ſpirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and therefore <hi>John</hi> writing to the Saints, warning them that they take heed of the Antichriſtian ſpirit, that they be not deceived, exhorteth them thus; let that therefore abide in you, which you have heard from the beginning; if that which you have heard from the beginning ſhall remain in you; ye alſo ſhall continue in the Son, and in the Father, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.24 read alſo for this purpoſe the whole chapter. Now that which they heard from the beginning, was the beginning Word of Chriſt, according to that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3, 4. which he delivered firſt of all to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that Chriſt dyed for our ſins, according to the Scripture, &amp;c. and the firſt principles of the word of God, which is the principles of the Doctrin of Chriſt, to wit, repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God, the Doctrin of Baptiſmes, and laying on of hands, and of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, and of eternal judgement, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. <hi>chap.</hi> 6.1, 2. now theſe principles of the teachings of Chriſt, came in being by and through Chriſt, being manifeſt in fleſh, his death and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:117938:38"/>as hath been ſhewed before; therefore whoſoever tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and abideth not in the Doctrin of Chriſt, hath not God, for he denyes Chriſt come in the fleſh, and ſo hee hath the ſpirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, and ſo having in part declared what is the ſpirit of Antichriſt, and who hath that ſpirit, I come now to the fourth thing, which is; that the Antichriſt will bee a ſingle perſon.</p>
            <p>And for the proof of this, firſt, conſider how the Antichriſt is ſet out in Scripture, in the ſingular number, not in the plural, as the MAN of ſin, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. not men, and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.16. is this the MAN that made the earth to tremble, and did ſhake the Kingdomes, the SON of the morning, and SON of Perdition? not Sons, the vile perſon, not perſons, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.12. there fell a great Star from Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.10. <hi>chap.</hi> 9.1. not Stars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> This in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. was fulfilled in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babel</hi> of <hi>Chaldee.</hi> Anſwer, That cannot be, for after this power that is there ſpoken of is faln, the whole World is at reſt, and is qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, they ſing for joy, yea the Firre-trees rejoyce at thee, and the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> ſaying, Since thou art layd down, no feller is come up againſt us, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7, 8. now the World did not injoy ſuch a reſt as is there ſpoken of, ſo as that no Feller came up againſt the people of God no more, for ſince the time of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and that Monarchies fall, there hath come up many fellers, or deſtroyers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the beleeving <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as is clear, that <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> againſt the Chriſtians; and again, the Apoſtle in 2 <hi>Thoſſ.</hi> 2. takes up the ſame words in ſubſtance, and applies them to the Man of Sin, which is the Antichriſt, therefore that in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cannot be fulfilled in <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar;</hi> for this compare <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.13, 14. with 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4. though he might be a type of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It appears that the Antichriſt will bee but one man (though many have his Spirit) becauſe it will ſuit beſt with his way of delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for he will pretend he is the very Chriſt, and will cauſe fire to come down from heaven on earth, in the ſight of men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.13. and ſo he will indeavour to imitate Chriſt in all things: for as the Lord Chriſt ſhall be revealed from heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that OBEY not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſo the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt will make fire come down from heaven in the ſight of men; ſo he will endeavour to make all the Scriptures that ſpeak of Chriſts
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:117938:39"/>coming, and of his reign, to meet upon him; SO his coming will be after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders, and with all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them that periſh, becauſe they receive not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 9, 10. ſo as there is the MAN Jeſus, the Chriſt the Son of the living God, which came in his Fathers Name, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.43. without ſin, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. ſo there will be the MAN of Sin, the Antichriſt, which will come in his own name, and profeſs to be the Chriſt, but will be directly an enemy againſt Chriſt and his people.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the Fifth thing, which is the manner of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts riſing, and by what means; for the clearing up of this, Firſt, conſider, that the Goſpel, and the way thereof, is to be purely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and the Ordinances rightly adminiſtred, and ſo the Angel is to fly in the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting Goſpel to preach unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every Nation, and Kindred, and Tongue, and People, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. and ſo the Goſpel being preached to the Nations, and the Ordinances adminiſtred in the good old way, according to the Scriptures, men come to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, as many are in theſe Nations, where the Kingly power is fallen that did ſupport the Whore, and would not give Liberty of Conſcience, ſo I ſay, as the Goſpel comes to be miniſtred, in the old way thereof, men come to bee inlightned, the power of the Whore falleth, and men ſlighting, and rejecting the truth, and alſo many of them that do receive and obey the truth, fall and depart from the Faith, and ſo receiving not the love of the truth that they might be ſaved; for this cauſe God doth, and will ſend them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould beleeve a lye, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. and ſo are given up to the Spirit of Antichriſt; and ſo as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the day of Chriſts coming ſhall not come, except there come a falling away firſt, and that Man of Sin be revealed, the Son of perdition, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7.8. <hi>chap.</hi> 2, 3. and ſo the Spirit ſpeaking ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that in latter times ſome ſhall depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing Spirits, and Doctrins of Devils, ſpeaking Lyes in Hypocriſie, having their Conſcience ſeared with a hot Iron, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to marry, &amp;c. as in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writing to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aints, in his Second <hi>Epiſt. chap.</hi> 2.1, 2. ſheweth, that there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction, and many ſhall follow their
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:117938:39"/>pernicious wicked ways, by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of; and <hi>chap.</hi> 3.3, 4. he ſaith, that there ſhould bee Scoffers, walking after their own luſts, ſaving, Where is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his coming, &amp;c? and ſo men tranſgreſſing, and abiding not in the Doctrin of Chriſt, fall from the faith of the Goſpel, and ſo the Spirit of God departeth from them, and an evil ſpirit is ſent unto them, which is the ſpirit of Antichriſt, ſo out from them that thus fall away, and go out from the Church, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. and ſo ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit, as <hi>Jude</hi> hath it, <hi>verſe</hi> 19. and alſo from them that have been enlightened<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to walk up in truth, and ſo reject the Counſel of God, as the Phariſees and Lawyers did, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.30. ſo I ſay from them that ſo fall away, and neglect to hear and obey the Goſpel, from them ariſeth the Antichriſt, or man of ſin.</p>
            <p>Again, the ſixth head of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, which is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall, or kingly power, hath and doth by the guidance of the Pope and the Nationall Miniſtry (which rides upon the beaſt, as hath been ſhewed) alwaies perſecuted men for their conſciences, and ſo hath let and hindred the Goſpel from being preached, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances from being rightly adminiſtred, and ſo the light of truth was exceedingly kept back, and but few received it, and them that did receive it, ſhe perſecuted, ſome ſhe put to death, others ſhe ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, or cauſed to flye into ſtrange Countries, and into howling Wilderneſſes, others impriſoned and fined, and ſo ſhe cometh to be drunken with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Jeſus, and ſo the Goſpel could not be declared in the pure way thereof, to every Nation, Kindred, Tongue, and People, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. and ſo alſo, if any did ariſe that had the ſpirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſhee took off him alſo, and ſo ſhee pluckt up much Wheat, and Tares alſo, contrary to that of <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.29, 30. let both grow together until Harveſt, and ſo forth: So the ſixth head of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Monarchy being rid upon, and guided by the Whore, did let the Goſpel from being preached, and the Antichriſt from riſing, and ſo I think that the ſixth head did hinder the coming in of the man of ſin in the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> time, for the Emperours being Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens then, perſecuted the Saints; and ſo that ſixth head ſupporting and carrying the Whore alſo, ſo as that it did let, and will let, until it bee taken out of the way, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.6, 7. but now the ſixth head being in part taken away, and the ſeventh head ariſing, hee giving
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:117938:40"/>ſome liberty of conſcience, the Goſpel is preached, and truth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, and many receive the knowledge of it, and obey it, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fall away from it, and ſo the ſpirit of Antichriſt ariſeth, and ſo the ſeventh head of the <hi>Roman</hi> Beaſt ſhall take away the ſixth head, and ſhall continue a ſhort ſpace, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10. and ſo the ten hornes alſo ſhall ariſe in one hour with the Beaſt that was, and is not, even hee is the eight, and is of the ſeventh; or is one of the ſeventh, <hi>verſe</hi> 11, 12. and ſo is the little horn that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.11, 24, 25. and the laſt power or Beaſt, the Antichriſt, the man of ſin, and ſo the ſeventh head and ten horns, or Kings giving liberty, the Servants of God ſound forth the truth as it is in Jeſus, miniſtring in the Goſpel glad tidings of the Kingdome to the Nations, men come to know the truth, and ſo are enlightened with it, and ſo many may come to ſhine as ſtars, and yet fall away as the Antichriſt, or man of ſin himſelf will be ſome notable man ſhining as a ſtar for a time, yet afterward falling from the truth, according to that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.10, 11. the third Angel ſounded, and there fell a great Star from Heaven, burning as it were a Lamp, and it fell upon the third part of the Rivers, and upon the fountains of waters and the name of the Star is called Wormwood, and the third part of the waters became Wormwood, and many men dyed of the waters, becauſe they were made bitter. So the man of ſin falls from the truth, or true Church, as a great Star from Heaven burning like a Lamp, through Satans transforming himſelf as into an Angel of light, and ſo fals upon the Rivers, and fountains of waters ſo that hee maketh them bitter; ſo that the ſweet promiſes of the Goſpel, and way of Chriſt, in which men ſhall bee made partakers of the Waters of life, and ſo made glad in the City of God; are ſo made bitter like Wormwood changing the taſte of them; ſo that many men dye of thoſe waters, according to that of <hi>Jude</hi> 12. twice dead, plucked up by the roots; and thus hee cauſeth men to fall, ſo that the third part of the Sun is ſmitten, and the third part of the Moon, and the third part of the Stars, ſo as a third part of them is darkened, and the day ſhone not for a third part of it, nor the night likewiſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.12. the Sun is here compared to the Church, becauſe the Church or Saints through Chriſt are ſaid to be the light of the World, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.14. and ſo <hi>Jacob</hi> who is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iſrael</hi> according to <hi>Joſephs</hi> dream, is compared to the Sun, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.9, 10. the Moon I take to bee the World, or the Whore, the falſe Church, which hath her light from the true Church, as the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:117938:40"/>Moon hath her light from the Sun; the Stars are the eminent teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. and this in the eight chapter before ſpoken of, is an allegory, becauſe the waters are ſaid to become Wormwood, and yet men drink of them, which cannot be, if they were made Wormwood, therefore it is allegoricall, that the Word of the Goſpel in the miniſtration of the Prophets, is compared to water, look <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.18, 19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. ſo then a many of the Church will fall from the faith, and the Stars, the elder or chief teachers alſo, and many of the World or falſe Church that ſhall be enlightened, and will not obey, ſhall bee darkened, and ſo ſhall loſe that light they have, and ſo ſhall be given up to groſs dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo after a great falling away from the truth; SO the man of ſin, the Antichriſt is revealed, and getteth the power and rule by flatteries; after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders, and with all deceivableneſſe of unrighteouſneſs, and SO oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or is worſhipped, ſo that HE as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3, 4, 9, 10. and ſo I come to the ſixth particular, which is, ſome of the great things that the man of ſin will do.</p>
            <p>Which in the firſt place take what <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith of him, ſetting him out by a little horn, <hi>chap.</hi> 7, 8.11, 24.25. he ſaith that he ſhall ſubdue three Kings, and he ſhall ſpeak GREAT words againſt the moſt high, and ſhall wear out the Saints of the moſt high, and think to change times and laws, and they ſhall bee given into his hand, untill a time, and times, and the dividing of times, and ſo he ſhall reign in full power, three years and a half, for time, is taken for one year, and times, two years, and half a time, is half a year, as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.25. ſome tranſlation reads for ſeven times, ſeven years; and ſo the woman cloathed with the Sun that flyes from him into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and is there three years and a half, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1.14. ſo he ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Saints of the moſt high, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.17. and the falſe Prophet cauſeth the firſt Beaſt whoſe deadly wound was healed, to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, and he doth great wonders, ſo that he maketh fire to come down from Heaven on the earth, in the ſight of men, and deceiveth them that dwell on the earth, by means of thoſe miracles, which he ſhall have power to do in the ſight of the Beaſt, ſaying, to them that dwell on the earth, that they ſhould make an image to the Beaſt which had the wound by a ſword, and did live, and he had power
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:117938:41"/>to give life, or breath to the Image of the Beaſt, that the Image of the Beaſt ſhould both ſpeak, and cauſe that as many as would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt, ſhould be killed, and he cauſeth all both ſmall and great, rich and poor, free and bond, to give a mark in their right hands, or in their foreheads, and that no man might buy or ſell, ſave hee that had the mark, or the name of the Beaſt, or the number of his name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11, to 18. ſo the Beaſt that had a wound with a ſword, that is, one of his ſeven heads was ſlain to death, yet ye having another, which is of the Seven, or one of the ſeven, and is the eight, and ſo liveth; and ſo it is the Beaſt that was, and is not, and yet is, and ſo the falſe Prophets ſhall by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, cauſe the World to worſhip the Beaſt, the man of ſin, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt as God ſitting in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. and cauſe as many as will not worſhip the Beaſt or his Image to bee killed, and ſo the fallen Star before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned which is the Beaſt, the Antichriſt aſcendeth out of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit, the key of the bottomleſs Pit being given him, he openeth the bottomleſs Pit, and then ariſeth a ſmoak out of the Pit, as the ſmoak of a great furnace, and the Sun, and the air will be darkened, by reaſon of the ſmoak of the Pit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7. <hi>chap.</hi> 9.1, 2. and neer the end of his reign, when the ſixth viall is poured, or pouring out, then ſhall come three unclean ſpirits like frogs out of the mouth of the Dragon, and out of the mouth of the Beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe Prophet, for they are the ſpirits of Devils, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king miracles, which go forth unto the Kings of the earth, and of the whole World, to gather them to battel of that great day of God Almighty; and hee gathered them together to a place called in the Hebrew tongue, <hi>Armageddon, Rev.</hi> 16.12, 13, 14, 16. which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> according to <hi>Joel</hi> 3.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. Multitudes, Multitudes in the Valley of Deciſion, or threſhing, for the day of the Lord is neer in the valley of deciſion, and ſo I come to the ſeventh particular, which is, the fall of the Beaſt, or man of ſin, and when, and by whom.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that the Lord will conſume him with the Spirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy him with the brightneſſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. ſo when the enemy ſhall come in as a flood, the Spirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a ſtandard againſt him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.19. and ſo when the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven, with ten thouſand of his Saints, to execute Judgement upon all, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince all that are ungodly among them, of all their ungodly deeds,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:117938:41"/>and of their hard ſpeeches, which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, <hi>Jud.</hi> 15. then the Sun and the Moon ſhall bee darkened, and the Stars ſhall withdraw their ſhining, the Lord alſo ſhall roar out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and utter his voice from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Heavens and the earth ſhall SHAKE, but the Lord will be the hope of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the ftrength of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Joel 3.15, 16. and in that day will the Lord make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a burdenſome ſtone for all People, all that burden themſelves with it, ſhall bee cut in peeces, though all the people of the EARTH bee gathered together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3, 4. then the Lord Jeſus (that DYED and ROSE again) himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, and with the voice of the Arch Angel, and with the Trumpe of God, and the dead in Chriſt ſhall ariſe firſt, then wee which are alive and remain, ſhall bee caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air, and ſo ſhall wee ever bee with the Lord, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14, 15, 16, 17. and ſo as <hi>Zechary</hi> hath it, the Lord my God ſhall come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all the Saints with him, <hi>chap.</hi> 14.5. and then the ten horns which received power as Kings in one hour with the Beaſt, the man of ſin; THESE have one mind, and ſhall give their power and ſtrength unto the Beaſt. THESE ſhall make war with the Lamb, and the Lamb ſhall overcome them, for hee is LORD OF LORDS, and KING OF KINGS, and they that are with him are called, and choſen, and faithfull, and ſo according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. the Lord Jeſus the KING OF KINGS, and LORD OF LORDS, with his armies which were in Heaven, following him upon white horſes, cloathed in fine linnen, white and clean, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends from Heaven againſt the Beaſt, the man of ſin, and the Kings of the earth, and their armies gathered together to make war againſt him that ſate on the horſe, the MAN Chriſt, and againſt his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the Beaſt was taken, and with him the falſe Prophet that wrought miracles before him, with which hee deceived them that had received the marke of the Beaſt, and them that worſhipped his Image; theſe both were caſt alive into a lake of fire burning with brimſtone, and the remnant were ſlain with the ſword of him that ſate upon the horſe, which ſword proceeded out of his mouth, and all foules were filled with their fleſh, ſo the Beaſt, the Antichriſt, the man of ſin, and the falſe Prophet which did work miracles before him, ſhall bee taken alive, and caſt into a lake of fire, burning with brimſtone, and ſo <hi>Tophet</hi> is ordained of old, yea, for the King it
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:117938:42"/>is prepared, hee hath made it deep and large, the pile thereof is fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord like a ſtream of brimſtone doth kindle it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. and ſo as men are threatned in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9, 10. that if they worſhip the Beaſt, or his Image, and receive his mark in their foreheads, or in their hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture, into the cup of his indignation, and hee ſhall bee tormented with fire and brimſtone, in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb. SO it ſhall come to paſs when the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſhall appear; and therefore take the 11 <hi>verſe,</hi> and the ſmoak of their torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever, and they have no reſt day nor night, who worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever receiveth the mark of his name, for this purpoſe, read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8, 19. and <hi>cha.</hi> 66.24. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.22, 23. THUS the Lord will mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie himſelf, and ſanctifie himſelf, and hee will bee known in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes of many nations, and they ſhall know that he is THE LORD, and then in that day ſhall his Servants ſay THIS IS THE LORD WE HAVE WAITED FOR HIM, WE WILL BE GLAD IN HIS SALVATION, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9.</p>
            <p>So then you may ſee that the Whore is not the Antichriſt that the Scripture ſpeaks of, for the Whore is ſet out in Scripture thus: <hi>As a Woman a Harlot, A falſe Church, As a Queen, the Mother of Harlots, And abominations of the earth;</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt is ſet out thus: <hi>A Man of Sin, The man that did ſhake Kingdoms, The Son of the Morning, The Son of Perdition.</hi> 2 The Sixth Head of the <hi>Roman</hi> Beaſt carryeth the Harlot, but the Antichriſt, the Man of Sin is the eighth and laſt Beaſt, as hath been ſhewed. 3 The Whore confeſſeth Chriſt come in the Fleſh, and hath a ſhew, and remembrance of his Ordinances, though ſhee have changed the ſubject and the manner; but the Antichriſt denies Chriſt come in the Fleſh, and his Ordinances that declare him come in the Fleſh, as it hath been ſhewed. 4. The Woman, the Harlot, and her Members that do worſhip according to her Traditions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, have ſpace given them to repent, and many do repent; but they that do worſhip the Beaſt, the Antichriſt, or receive his Mark in their right hand, or in their fore-head, they cannot repent, they muſt drink of the wine of the Wrath of God, &amp;c. as it is, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 14.9, 10. and alſo in chap. 16. they repented not of their deeds, verſ. 11. note that the firſt Vial is poured out upon the earth, and the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:117938:42"/>men that had the mark of the Beaſt, and worſhipped his Image, are plagued; therefore none of the Vials are poured out until the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt reigneth, verſ. 1, 2. 5. The Ten Horns hate the Whore, and deſtroy her, and make her deſolate, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. but the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is taken alive, when the Lord cometh, and puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, in a Lake of fire, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. And ſo to draw to a concluſion, I do deſire all men to take heed to the Scriptures of the Prophets and Apoſtles, for they are able to make men wiſe unto Salvation and if men ſpeak not according to the Law and Teſtament, it is becauſe they have no light in them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. O give heed to the moſt ſure word of the Prophets, as unto a light ſhining in a dark place, until the Day of Chriſt dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in your hearts, noting diligently all things that are ſpoken of; that muſt come to paſs, for when the ſigns concerning Chriſts coming are come to paſs, the day of Chriſts perſonal appearing will dawn.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Is there ſuch a ſpirit of deluſion among men, wherein is a myſtery of iniquity? then let all take heed, that they ſeek the Lord while he may be found, and to kiſs the Son leaſt he be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and yee periſh in the way. O do not neglect to read, and know, and ſearch the Scriptures, and walk up in that you do know; bee not deceived, God will not be mocked; what a man ſoweth that ſhall he reap, for he that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption, but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap life everlaſting, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Is it ſo that God doth, and will give up men to a ſpirit of deluſion, that they ſhould beleeve a Lye, that they all might be damned who beleeved not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs? then be exhorted from hence to forſake all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ways in converſation, and all whoriſh inventions of men in point of Worſhip, for if <hi>Moſes</hi> Law be aboliſhed, which was given to him by the Lord, let no man think that he ſhall be excuſed, if he worſhip according to mens inventions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Let all the Saints conſider, and lay to heart what hath been ſpoken, and ſearch the Scriptures, that they may be informed what is to come to paſs, and ſo according to Chriſts exhortation, in <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36. watch yee therefore, and pray always, that yee may be accounted worthy to eſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſs, and to ſtand before the Son of Man; O give all diligence to adde to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:117938:43"/>your faith vertue, and to vertue knowledge, and to knowledge temperance, and to temperance patience, and to patience godlineſs, and to godlineſs brotherly kindneſs, and to brotherly kindneſs love; let theſe things be in you and abound, give diligence to make your calling and election ſure, be not weary of well-doing, for you ſhall reap in due time if you faint not; grow in grace, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; to him be glory both now and for ever, So be it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117938:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
